all right we rolling we're rolling we
get to see how you guys do this it's
kind of interesting we usually have pump
up music but I feel pumped up we can do
that we got a turntable here oh I I saw
your turntable that's beautiful what do
you want to hear no we're starting Ben's
keeping us on track who got the
truth is it you is it you is it who got
the truth
now is it you is it you is it you sit me
down say stra another story on the way
got the TR welcome to season 14 episode
5 of acquired the podcast about great
companies and the stories and playbooks
behind them I'm Ben Gilbert I'm David
renthal and we are your hosts 7 years
ago David and I did an episode on the
Starbucks IPO just the IPO that episode
was a mere 1 hour and 24 minutes and
Starbucks is a 90 billion institution in
our world that deserves the full
acquired treatment what were we thinking
well it actually was Amateur hour back
then David got to start somewhere well
today we have a very special third
co-host to discuss this third place
Howard Schultz Howard started working at
the small chain of three Starbucks
stores in 1982 eventually buying it and
becoming CEO as you probably know he is
effectively the founder of the Starbucks
we know today that exists on every
corner of the Earth I come to you David
and listeners as an unabashed Starbucks
fan in this tumultuous time for the
company I am absolutely pulling for them
in every way possible and that is going
to come through in our conversation you
may have seen the news recently that
they had a very rough last quarter with
a key metric that you may remember from
previous episodes as same store sales
these dropped and their stock price
plummeted as a result this is on top of
a tumultuous pandemic era and some of
their stores unionized and a change in
leadership we thought that this would be
the perfect time to sit down with Howard
and unpack why did Starbucks work in the
first place and how did it work at such
Grand scale what can other Founders and
Business Leaders learn from what got
them here and although he is no longer
CEO where do they go now it really is
incredible one of the very very small
number of food and beverage
establishments that has scaled to the
entire world yeah most of those types of
Concepts do not work in different
countries and continents but Starbucks
is different today they're in over 80
countries with 39,000 stores across the
world they're even huge in China a
country that didn't consume very much
coffee until Starbucks arrived they are
a bank scale financial institution as
well at any given time Starbucks holds
$1.7 billion doar that customers have
loaded onto gift cards but not yet spent
so how did they go from one store
selling beans not even drinks and cups
Just beans beans to the default meeting
place in communities everywhere today we
tell that story and listeners this
episode has video we recorded it in
person in Seattle at the Schultz family
foundation and you can watch it on
YouTube all right well listeners we have
a gigantic announcement for you yes save
the date if you love acquired you are
going to want to be physically in the
city of San Francisco on Tuesday
September 10th 2024
and we can't say much you know about
every detail of it just yet but it will
be the biggest thing that acquired has
ever done it'll be in partnership with
our good friends at JP Morgan payments
so mark your calendars now save the date
and if you want to be first to know
details you can sign up at acquired.
fmsf or click the link in the show notes
speaking of JP Morgan payments just like
how we say every company has a story
every company's story is powered by
payments and J Morgan payments is a part
of so many companies Journeys from seed
to IPO and Beyond and if you want more
from David and I you should check out
our second show aq2 where we interview
Founders investors and experts often as
deeper dives into topics that we covered
on the main show recent episodes have
been awesome with the CEO and the
founder of synopsis of starfish space
further exploring the space industry and
we've got some great stuff in payments
coming up next too we do all right so
with that this show is not investment
advice David and I may have investments
in the companies that we discuss and
this show is for informational and
entertainment purposes only onto our
episode with Howard
Schultz well I do have to tell you and I
think I've told you this off camera for
the last almost 10 years every single
day starts with a spinach and feder app
I assume there are other people like me
in the world but it's always an iced
almond milk latte with whipped cream and
a spinach and feter wrap and so thank
you for uh powering approximately third
of the cells in my
body that's a great start I also here's
another stat that David you've done the
math on I have done the math I exported
all of my credit card transactions since
2011 of course you did and I wish I had
more history than that but that was the
oldest I could get I've spent
$23,000 at Starbucks since 2011 oh God
okay so we want to start with Starbucks
1.0 and listeners May know that there
were three founders of Starbucks yes
none of which were named Howard Schultz
correct so take us back you know in the
Starbucks prehistory before you arrived
how did the company start well since I
wasn't there this is what I know there
were three founders Jerry Baldwin Zev
seagull and Gordon
balker and the story that was told to me
is that one or both of them were going
to school in California in the B area
and they became enamored with Pete's
Coffee Company uh which Alfred Pete
Alfred Pete was you know more than
anyone else in the history of coffee in
America was the true Pioneer he
brought specialy coffee a Raba coffee to
Northern
California and Jerry Baldwin and Zev
became so interested and intrigued with
what pets was doing and given the fact
that they were from seatt attle decided
they would try and bring Starbucks
coffee in the form of Starbucks to
Seattle Washington now what is not known
is that when Starbucks opened in the
Pike Place Market in
1971 they were using Pete's Coffee
really no one knows that that's new WoW
because they they were not roasting
coffee so they were bringing coffee from
s Francisco to Seattle they were not
calling it Pete's they were calling it
Starbucks so it was Pete's Coffee and
Starbucks yeah yeah again I wasn't there
but that's kind of the
folklore after the three
founders built that store open that
store uh I I get the sense that there
was some kind of Fallout between the
three of them and Zev seagull eventually
left the
company that brings us to
1979 1980 around that time when I came
to Seattle Washington for the first time
so I was working for a Swedish
housewares company based in Sweden
called Hammer plast that company had a
beautiful non-electric coffee maker kind
of a thermal unit and we had a big
customer in Macy's in Northern
California and I was in California on a
sales call and I had heard that there
was a small company in Seattle
Washington was buying a lot of this
product so given the fact I'd never been
to Seattle I was already on the west
coast I figured I'd come to Seattle and
see what was going on was Starbucks
buying it for use in they were selling
it in their store now but here's the
thing this was a consumer device yeah
yeah but you have to remember Starbucks
Coffee Company from 1971 until around
8586 only sold pounds of coffee there
was no beverage that's you know we're
going to get into the epiphany of that
of course and so I walked into the Pike
Place store for the first time on a
beautiful day just like this the sun was
out there was snow on the mountains the
clean fresh air and I walked into the
Pik Place Market and I walked into the
Starbucks store and I was blown away by
the experience the the romance of coffee
the
education and it just spoke to me I had
never met Jerry Baldin the founder who
was the CEO at the time and I became
interested and intrigued with with what
Starbucks was doing and asked if I could
meet Jerry one thing led to another I
met Jerry Baldwin we really hit it off
and we established kind of a vendor
customer relationship over a course of a
year or so Starbucks had three stores at
the time only three and over the course
of the next year or so I became more and
more interested and intrigued with the
possibility of leaving New York City
Sher and I were dating we not married
and I kind of maneuvered my way into a
job working for Starbucks and so Sherry
and I drove to Seattle Washington on
Labor Day weekend in our old Audi car
with a golden
retriever and we came here because I was
offered the job as the head of marketing
for Starbucks when they were getting
ready to open their fourth store in
1982 still just selling beans only beans
that's the whole yeah still
the interest that the company had in me
at the time I think was they were really
interested in expanding but their their
dream or or the plan at the time was
could we expand to Portland
Oregon remember so it was a tiny company
was Grand ambition yeah and I never had
any idea of course that what was about
to happen and unfold of the subsequent
years but that was I arrived in 1982 as
a head of marketing so when you and
Sherry arrived drive here like what was
the coffee landscape I mean there were
these three soon to be four Starbucks
Bean stores here in Seattle Alfred Pete
was down in the Bay
Area but what was Coffee Culture I mean
it was it was like folders in Maxwell
House right yeah it was uh it was di
minimist it was another coffee company
which was Seattle's Best Coffee which
was another retailer that was kind of at
the same size and scale at Starbucks
both equal at the same time but you
couldn't get a New York Times in Seattle
in 1982 83 it was not no good food to
speak of and Starbucks was a true
Pioneer where they were
educating customer after customer about
what good coffee tastes like and the
pipe Place Market gave them an
interesting vehicle because of of the
tur and so Starbucks actually started
establishing a mail order business as a
result of all the people who were coming
into Seattle and I think if I remember
there was so many points that I can
remember where people were talking about
Starbucks Way outside of Seattle as if
it was some kind of iconic big company I
think people came to Seattle is this it
this is you know the 8900 Foot Store in
Seattle Washington in Pike Place Market
this is the Mecca and so tourists would
come they would buy a bag and then they
would fill out some kind of information
so I'd like to I'd like to have this
mailed to me gr mail bus in my city yeah
that's what happened and because coffee
has a shelf life of basically a week to
10 days and we didn't have a vacuum bag
at that time we were shipping small
amounts because to Jerry Baldwin's
credit he had such a fastidious point of
view about quality and freshness and I
think that had a huge impact on me but
this couldn't have been like a great
business you're shipping small amounts
the logistics costs you know the scale
like this was a small business but the
equity of the brand even back then was
much larger than the size of the
business and the opportunity that I saw
even when we had four or five stores was
well beyond Portland Oregon and I was
always kind of pushing we can do so much
more and then the whole thing blew up
for me when I went to Italy in 83 okay
so before the Italy trip I just want to
really contextualize coffee and
America I think coffee had been
declining since like 1940 still part of
the American culture but it's not that
it's on the way out but there's nothing
new or interesting except for this
little segment of specially coffee which
was Tiny and I think what you've just
described the reason for that is the
coffee was terrible it was instant
coffee stale coffee and primarily
robusta beans which is the lowgrade
coffee that Starbucks was never never
involved in yeah walk us through the two
types of beans there's mainly two types
of agricultural coffee grown for
commercial use robusta beans low-end
coffee primarily and instant coffee and
high-grade arabica coffee but even
within the arabica coffee there's
significant segments of quality and
integrity and Starbucks was has always
played from 1971 to today at the highest
level and my understanding from our
research is that the a market really
developed as you say with the instant
coffee market and that was kind of a
product of World War II right it was
like Hey we got to get the troops this
product to survive and so we just need a
lot of beans and we need to ground them
up and create this instant product I
believe Maxwell House was involved in
inventing yeah you're exactly right I
mean it was just Fuel and bitter acidic
and yeah and that's I think World War II
and the gis were kind of the impetus for
that kind of quality coffee or not
quality coffee to exist and have any
kind of run after the war so you show up
at Starbucks you know you know a little
bit about the market because you've been
a A supplier of theirs but you happen to
be a pretty talented salesman from your
your time at Xerox and I want to make a
tie here our previous episode was the
Microsoft episode or at least Microsoft
volume one you were selling word
processors made by Xerox tell me what
word processors were in the mid 70s
so my territory was 42nd to 48th Street
from Fifth Avenue to the river and I had
to make 50 cold calls physical cold
calls a
day that was a job the Xerox job taught
me incredible amounts about not only
selling but
humility humility because the rejection
every day was so sign significant and
you put on your suit and tie and you go
in an office building there's no
security at that time just go in and you
go from the top floor to the bottom and
then there were other people selling
other products who are doing the exact
same thing and you had to get by the
receptionist I was making ,000 a month
and living at home when I
started okay the word processor was a
big machine in which you are editing on
that machine to basically create a
letter and does it have a screen or is
like a typewriter no it's a typewriter
no screen it's like a typewriter with
like a with a little bit of cash right
so you could like exctly fix mistakes
for one line right yeah the job at Xerox
at the time was like working for Google
I mean Xerox and IBM were the two
pillars of technology and high-tech
companies you told somebody you working
at Xerox you had a whole different
patina that you were wow that's working
for zerox Wow and so you quitting well
Hammer plast but you know quitting what
seemed like a I hated it stable of
pretty good jobs to drive across the
country to provincial little Seattle I
mean that's that's
nuts I knew after a couple of years if I
stayed at Xerox for a a longer period of
time I was going to be locked in there
but I'll tell you the story that got me
to realize I've got to get out of here
at the end of the year the performance
appraisal at Xerox was basically a
scorecard from 1 to five so you'd have a
qualitative discussion with your manager
and then he would give you a
number and when I got a
three I said I you know I just saying to
myself I worked all year I just had an
performance appr for my manager and I'm
a three this is amazing Howard Schultz
got a three I got a three I got a three
inspiration for all entrepreneur I got a
three and as soon as I got the three I
swear at that moment I knew I've got to
get out of here and that's when I
started putting myself in a position of
meet other opportunities and by and
large I was able to get the hammer plast
job which was the general manager of the
company which was based in Sweden in the
US but I was a three do you think having
that background at Xerox did that give
you a piece of perspective that helped
build Starbucks to what it is
today when I hear the question I I have
to go back to my childhood and think
everything that have experienced growing
up in the
projects in more or less a dysfunctional
family because of the the pressure of
Money Getting the Xerox
opportunity and having some level of
success but realizing I wanted
more the humility which came with
rejection the shame I had as a poor kid
living in the projects all of that I
think crystallized in me and I give Sher
so much credit in realizing that
together we wanted to build a different
kind of life and gave me the Courage the
conviction and um the drive to try and
do something that I felt I was destined
to do I didn't know what it was I
certainly didn't know moving to Seattle
was going to create the opportunity of a
lifetime but I always felt I had to get
out of that station in life where I was
positioned not to get to the level that
I thought I I deserve to be I don't
think it is common with someone for your
background poor kid in the projects
coming from nothing to get a great job
two great jobs and be wildly
dissatisfied and not feel like I've made
it but rather no there's got to be
something more than this there's
something deep inside you that caused
you to be willing to take take a risk I
was really insecure about not
succeeding and I didn't view what I was
doing as the success that I was not
destined for that's that sounds wrong
that that I had the appetite for all
right so we're getting to the big risk
so the year takes over to 1983 yeah you
are sent or maybe you asked to go to an
international housewares conference in
Milan yeah what do you discover so I
went to a trade show called
machf uh it's big convention center and
a it's a giant houseware show with
equipment and all kinds of stuff and I I
was staying at a a relatively cheap
hotel in walking distant to the
convention center I get out of the hotel
I'd never been to Italy before and I am
all of a sudden being intercepted with
the physical manifestation of one coffee
bar after after another in the business
that I'm supposed to be in but it wasn't
the business that Starbucks was in and I
walk in like a normal person that's
never seen this before and I am just
like I'm in a black and white movie and
all of a sudden everything was color and
it was so
rich I couldn't get enough of it and I
just went from one to the other to the
other to the other and
I I was just blown away and more or less
raced back to America sat down with
Jerry and Gordon and said holy
we got happening in in Italy is the
business that Starbucks has to be in and
they had seen it they've been Italy and
they said no that's not what we want to
do and I just said seriously and I
banged on the door for two years and in
two years they finally let me open up a
coffee bar on the corner of fourth and
spring in Seattle and it was the sixth
Starbucks store and out of about 1,200
square fet I got 100 feet and I designed
and opened the coffee bar worked behind
the counter as a barista and Starbucks
probably had two to 300 customers a day
selling hobing coffee we were at 500 in
a week with introducing lattes and
cappuccino to the an espresso and
there's nowhere else no one in Seattle
had it well get
had it and that was Dave olon and after
a few months or six months or so Jerry
said I don't want to repeat this I don't
want to do it I don't want to be in the
restaurant business yeah what was the
objection was it the he he just he
stigma of the restaurant business I mean
I don't want to speak for Jerry I have
so much respect for him but he didn't
think it was clean he didn't like it now
between 83 and
885 Jerry Baldwin because of his love of
pets
and his relation with Alfred Pete had an
opportunity for Starbucks to acquire
Pete's Coffee company and they
did
unfortunately Starbucks buys pets and
they get into financial trouble and so
really at this point it was like their
Mentor was retiring this person who was
a steward of the industry we operating
six points of retail distribution in
Seattle for our beans why don't we just
buy your effectively the same business
but in Northern California keep them SE
well it's important to know that between
the opening of the fourth and spring
coffee bar inside of Starbucks Starbucks
number six yeah and Jerry and Gordon
saying we don't want to repeat this I
was so frustrated I said I'm going to
leave
Starbucks and what did I do I had no
money to open up a coffee store so Jerry
says Starbucks does not want to open up
coffee bars but we will in invest in il
jali which was the company you started
too yeah so before they get into
financial trouble Starbucks is an
investor I've always thought he did that
so I would sell and Market Starbucks
coffee in the coffee bar which I would
have done anyway so Starbucks makes an
investment a couple of people that we
know make an investment but I didn't
have enough money so I go to see two
Italian companies I've never told this
one is the espresso company
FMA and one is the large Italian Coffee
Company lavat oh yeah and I asked them
both to invest in my
idea and both of them turned me down so
at this point you're in Italy you're
trying to get ideas and investors for
what would become IL Al for the first Al
and only Starbucks and a couple other
people have committed but I didn't have
enough money I still I needed more money
huh and you were raising 1.6 million
about 1 Point yeah 1.6 1.7 million and
they said you know no one is going
to buy Italian espresso in Seattle or In
America which is stupid because you
watched it happen like I ran this store
for six months and like it was flying
you know yeah they didn't want to do it
so they they lva and FMA just get that
on the record turned me down okay
they'll deny it that's a fact so then I
you know go back to the US I'm trying to
raise money and I I hit the three Titans
in
Seattle Jack beroya Herman sharkowski
and Sam
strong three of the leading citizens of
Seattle Washington at the time and the
three of them have a little bit of an
investment together and other things and
they say we're going to believe in you
and they take me over the the hump wow
okay and we opened three ill jali's two
in Seattle one in Vancouver BC
and all three are doing well all three
but I didn't have enough money to expand
and needing the money to expand just to
pause on that for a minute
business-wise obviously coffee bars are
a much better business long term than
coffee beans but probably more Capital
intensive right you need more staff yeah
more labor yes but the stores weren't
that expensive to open because they were
small less than a th000 square fet and
we we understood how to do it and I was
working as a barista with Dave Olson and
other people keep the cost down we were
behind the counter and I had no salary I
had no salary for almost two years wow
while Sher was working and pregnant with
our first child so looking increasingly
worse from a traditional perspective of
leaving a high quality job moving across
the country then just a couple years
later you are not making any money again
well raising millions of dollars to try
to start your own business it gets
worse Sherry is sick seven months
pregnant she's working her parents
visits y they're from Ohio father asked
me to take a walk oh no as godess my way
is true story take a walk and he says
uh whatever you're doing I respect it
but it's not a job it's a hobby you need
to get a
job my daughter's pregnant she's working
you're not I start crying I bet so
embarrassed and uh I come home at 3 4:00
in the afternoon whatever it is I don't
say a
word completely shaken by the whole
conversation her parents go to bed after
dinner I'm sitting with Sherry and I
said I got to tell you something to
happen she was so angry at her dad and
so upset and she said there's no way
we're turning around we're we are going
so she is the glue to everything that's
happened
and I don't know if she've ever had a
conversation with her father I'm sure
she did I don't but the whole thing
could have been over and that would have
been a very understandable response of
Sher said I'm you know I wasn't going to
say anything but you know look at our
situation objectively here putting
ourselves in your father in-law's shoes
how could you not feel that way for your
daughter and her impending family yeah
and and her father was a great guy and
uh I understood but I was embarrassed
and humiliated How can I not be mean I
guess that's another dimension here too
this was not 2024 it's not like being an
entrepreneur was a you know glorified
profession here in a business that he
clearly did not understand you know
coffee store the other interesting thing
to point out around this time is for the
people who were seeking high-risk
business Investments you know this is
the late 80s it's time to look at Tech
like we're now 12 years into Microsoft
apples four years past the
Macintosh and I'm I'm trying you're
trying to raise money for a coffee house
chain with names that people couldn't
pronounce and serving it in a paper
cup to go that does not sound Innovative
to me I don't know why I'm putting my
risk Capital into your yeah you know I
would bring investors to the two or
three stores and I would make sure there
was a fair amount of people in the space
and that's when I started talking
about the language of community in the
third place and that's what I saw in
Italy the unlock and the epiphany of
course it was the romance of espresso
but it was the sense of community and
that is what was happening very early on
in the two stores in Seattle and the one
in Vancouver you could see it what would
people do after they bought the coffee
you said these are very small places
they would stand up because the two
stores didn't have seating right away
they would stand up at the coffee bar at
the window on Columbia Center and it was
at at 8 9:00 in the morning they were
hanging out there and then they after
late morning they were coming back and
you could just feel the relationship
that people were having with one another
around human
connection I know it sounds trite but I
I could see it back then and as I was
talking to people about the investment
opportunity I was pointing out like look
what's happening here there's something
happening there's some magic going on
here it's not just the Cofe coffee the
coffee was the
conduit all right so we're at the
pivotal moment Starbucks and petza gets
into financial trouble and the debt to
equity was north of 6 to1 for a company
was
Tiny Jerry comes to me and
says Jane and I his wife are going to
move to California and we're gonna keep
Pete's and I'm going to sell
Starbucks and my heart is pounding I
said okay and then he finish it and he
says I think you're the person to buy
Starbucks I said that's fantastic but I
don't have any money you get to give it
to me no money how much is it $3.8
million now we're in 86
87 now we get into a story I have told
but not 100% because I protected the guy
but I'm going to tell it I go out to
raise money I'm having a hard time so
Jerry gave me about I think he gave me
99 days to raise $3.8
million around the second month he just
came to me and said where are you with
all this and I I think I had about half
of it raised I might have fibd a bit and
said I had a little bit more but I I
didn't I had about half and he lays a
bomb on me and says Howard listen we're
in a tight situation here and one of
your
investors has put a cash all cash offer
on the table with with no due diligence
and wants to close right away for him to
take it over not you yeah yeah I'm out
I'd be out and I said who is
it and he told me I'll save that and I'm
absolutely annihilated crushed because I
didn't have the wherewithal and I could
just Envision as soon as I heard that
name I knew was
over I was in a basketball league at the
Seattle Club
I'm playing basketball that night my
good friend Scott Greenberg who's an
attorney at uh a Prestige firm in
Seattle the gates
firm I'm basically crying to him after
the game and telling him the story and
he says you got to come to the office
tomorrow and meet our senior partner and
tell him the story Bill Gates
Senior I said well a Titan incredible
the other we foreshadowed this m episode
there were there were three Titans there
but here is the Titan and Bill was 6'7
he's 6' s a mountain of a man and very
imposing so 9:00 in the
morning I put a suit
on I must have been sweating through my
shirt I was just so anxious so nervous
and at the same time so scared about
what's going to happen I go in
there and I I I must have been trembling
I I I I was is so nervous I tell him
exactly what I just told him and he
interrupts me and says Howard I'm just
going to ask you two questions is
everything you told me
true I said Mr Gates yes have you left
anything out
no and he says come back in an
hour and I said okay to do what he says
I'll see you in an hour and so we walk
out and walking around I think we
probably went to went to Columbia Center
to get a coffee and come back and go
back with Scott and Mr Gat says Scott
I'm going to see how we're alone and
Scott Le now I'm alone in his office I
hardly sit down and he says we're going
for a
walk and I said where are we going and
he says we're going to
see the
man who was Sam strum
one of your investors one of the
investors we walk across the street to
the reineer tower the Old rineer Tower I
think Sam had one of the biggest offices
we walk in there and I swear even though
it's so many years later I have a
perfect Vivid account for what took
place Sam is sitting behind his desk and
this is what happened because it was 5
minutes Bill
Gates remember remember he's a huge guy
leans over to the desk with his hands on
Sam's desk and says I don't know what
you are planning but whatever it is it's
not going to
happen wow and he says Howard Schultz is
going to acquire Starbucks coffee
company and he's never going to hear
from you
again that was
it and we walk out
out that's it that's the whole thing and
so did you hear from Jerry that the bid
had been dropped we walk out and I say
to Mr one little problem you still need
the money right yes I say to Mr G what
what what just happened and he said
you're going to buy Starbucks Coffee
Company and my son and I are going to
help you wow
H and we raised the
money and that's the story I never spoke
to Sam strum again I've never mentioned
his name publicly I never mentioned his
name in his book and I say it
respectfully I'm not trying to but
that's the story and Sam I mean for for
anyone who doesn't live in the Seattle
area his name is on buildings and
community centers I mean this revered
philanthropist I actually don't know his
business background how did he become
the Titan that he was he was involved in
real estate and also in those auto
stores how did you get him off the ill
joural cap table like wasn't he an
investor still he he was he and his
family were investors to the end until
they got out oh wow wow till they got
out wow Looking Back Now what do you
think happened did he have any
legitimate criticisms of you as running
the company no he had he had a henchman
who was his money guy who figured out we
we could just take this company and what
do we need Howard Schultz for who is
this young
kid and he and Sam had experience with
retail with those auto stores I see so
he could install some Professional
Management from Venture run the Playbook
yeah it would have been over but the
thing about Bill Gates is I saw him
socially a 100 plus
times he never ever said anything public
about what he did he never took credit
for it so for listeners uh Howard's told
this elsewhere but you spoke at the
Microsoft CEO Summit you recounted the
story to you know the Fortune 500 CEOs
and um Bill Gates III you know Microsoft
founder comes up to you afterwards and
says um yeah who was the guy but Bill
did not know the whole story he didn't
know any of it he didn't know what his
father had done for me he's hearing it
for the first time and this is you know
2015 or something so Starbucks like you
would think no he didn't know someone
would want to tell their family I played
some significant role in this but that's
not the type of guy he was Bill Gates
Senor never told us Soul what he did for
me wow again
humility incredible lesson about
humility it's amazing yeah and so were
Bill Gates Senior and Bill Gates II
investors in that 3.8 Million Dollar
Round Bill senior was but I don't know
if it was part of Bill or yeah Microsoft
in interesting um so I asked Sherry
about this When I Was preparing for the
episode and her recollection was it was
something
like one to two weeks before the 3month
exclusivity for you was going to be up
and so you're basically like this event
happens but now you need to come up with
the money and you have this unbelievably
short period of time to do so and so she
said that you were calling everybody you
knew she was calling her clients cuz
she's a designer calling her clients
trying to just you know find pockets of
50k here 100K there anywhere you could
to make it happen but I had another
Angel who helped me by the name of Jack
Rogers who became a lifelong friend who
passed away a couple years ago he was
part of an investor group and he brought
them along so the acquisition goes
through yeah August of ' 87 yeah we
bought the six Starbucks stores we had
the three old ill jali and there were
two stores under construction so at the
end of the calendar year we had 11
stores and 100 employees in
1987 all in the Northwest yeah meanwhile
the original Starbucks folks they've now
gone down to cnia went to California
when did Pete's open coffee bars uh many
many years later ah so they you weren't
competing away no but this is one of the
great observations David ill joural buys
the Starbucks stores rebrands ill joural
incorporated as the Starbucks
Corporation yeah and the original
Starbucks buys you know had owned pets
and now needs a new name so it rebrands
the company pets so pets was actually
Starbucks Starbucks was actually ilj yes
it's amazing
some stats just for listeners to
understand the gravity of the situation
uh for the initial 1.6 million that you
raised for ill joural you talked to 242
investors 2117 of which said no so
anybody who's griping about their
fundraising journey and you know those
are rookie numbers get but you asked me
a question earlier about what did the
years at Xerox teach me so the rejection
I was going through the Italians turned
me down people the US turn me down
nobody would believe in the idea it was
like I was Co calling again at Xerox the
other thing that is worth pointing out
is the
Starbucks company with the six stores
when they bought pets with that six to1
debt to equity ratio basically backed
themselves into a corner where now they
had these big Debt Service payments to
make there was really no risk they could
take or innovation that they could do
because the whole business needed to
spit out a certain amount of cash every
month so they could pay down the debt
and so when you're in that situation
Starbucks in the 40 years ahead from
this point in the story has tried all
sorts of crazy things to become the
business that it is today and when you
first created this combined company you
were pretty religious about no debt no
debt I I want any debt again because of
my childood I was going to ask you was
that informed by the the what you had
seen with the Starbucks situation your
child no it it's total my childhood my
parents were always in debt bill
collectors were always calling and uh no
there was we never had any debt the
entire time never this is probably a
good point in time to talk about the
business model a little bit you've
alluded to kind of a stigma at least
among potential investors and the
original Starbucks founders of like the
restaurant business what did the
economics of the business of the coffee
bar business look like when you bought
the Starbucks stores so what did we buy
we had the stores we had the brand name
and we had a roasting facility on
Airport Way in Seattle the ability to
source and roast
coffee and put that through the supply
chain of a beverage gave us probably at
the time an 80% gross margin wow yeah
that is not the the quote unquote
restaurant business that people are
imagining and I could begin to see even
early on the creative nature of
frequency where I can see what was going
on here is people were not coming for
coffee in the morning anymore they were
starting the morning Rush was getting
bigger the need for more labor and I
could sense that the business that
Starbucks was in was going to be
significantly in the back and the
beverage and the Romance of the theater
and the third place was the hero
didn't take us long to realize we had
the beginning of lightning in the bottle
even the best most successful restaurant
you could possibly imagine how many
times are their most loyal customers
going to come there in a week yeah well
there were I think there was a time in
the Northwest when we were really at our
Peak where the average customer was
coming 18 times a month I should
rephrase it maybe the most loyal was
coming 18 times a month there's some
magic to this idea that it's not a
terribly expensive item I think I saw
some research that said that it's you
know sub 1% of someone's house household
income and often far less than that but
it is repeat and it is high gross margin
and so when you say lightning in a
bottle there's a cultural lightning in a
bottle but there's also this like
ridiculous business model where the way
it shows up is your stores basically
from this point forward for all of
Starbucks's life you'd build a new store
and the profits from that store would
totally cover the cost within 2 years
years and often a year and a half but
I'll tell you the economic model that we
we applied to every single store we were
opening you know by the way I chose the
first 500 locations myself so I was in
it in so many ways but the the economic
model in Wall Street when we went public
in '92 now I'm just when they when they
heard the model said well we never seen
a model like that and the model
basically was a sales to investment
ratio of
2:1 and a operating profit of 20% so
what does that mean sales to investment
ratio so if the sales were a million
dollars the investment was 500,000 met
just the sales to invest had to be a two
to one wow in year one of operation yes
and the and and the the operating profit
was was north of
20% wow but cash on cast return was so
yeah you get that two years or last
payback the retail world had never seen
a model like this before there was no
physical storefront that could had this
business model before this early on it
became clear to that customers were also
starting to customize the beverage on
their
own so we were just Bria was behind a
counter and somebody would say can I can
you put something else in there yeah
what do you want and then so that just
started you know the average ticket
started growing as a result of the
customers personalizing and customizing
their beverage and to be clear like the
era of Starbucks we are in right now you
produce drip coffee and you produce es
espresso you can put that espresso in
frothed milk and those that's basically
your options yeah like none of this you
know yeah exactly but can I tell you a
mistake I made please please when ilali
was getting ready to open the standard
cup in the world was that terrible
Styrofoam cup that is used in diners in
New York City remember that cup yeah I
put boiling water into that cup five
minutes later the cup is starting to
turn like a golden color because of the
chemical that can't be good for your
insides or the taste of the
cough and so we had to find we had to
change the cup this was such a smart
move in retrospect but we were just
trying to figure out now no one in
America that is in the paper business
had any kind of cup or lid that was
compatible with what I was trying to do
in fact they didn't understand it why
not just use the cup that exist is no
because it doesn't taste good and it
doesn't feel right right why go to the
trouble of you know this perfected roast
of these beautifully source to rabika
beans from all these Farmers if you're
going to pour it into styrofoam yeah
okay people think you were a hippie like
when you were tell these like are you
this dismiss me
so we went to Chicago to the
International Paper company and they had
a
cup but the cup didn't have a
lid a compatible lid and so we found
they found a lid that beautiful sip lid
which is now ubiquitous in the world
Howard SCH should have said to them I
want an exclusive on that
lid because that lid became the standard
for the world if I would have just
understood that the other thing I didn't
do is we introduced cafe latte to the to
America we didn't trademark it you know
we trademarked Frappuccino later on but
we didn't trademark cafe latte this you
know wasn't thinking yeah you got enough
right you don't need to get them all
right no I I just I missed it when uh
the
sizing Grande ventti oh that was a the
hidden Traina yeah right when did that
start there was a brilliant brilliant
guy who was the architect of the name
Starbucks named Terry Heckler in Seattle
and he's a fantastic design guy and
we're just sitting one day and I just
talking about the importance of language
we got to get the language right we got
the cup got to get the language and we
just started talking about changing it
from The Pedestrian words of small
medium large to what it became which was
short tall and
Grande people made fun of it but they
loved it was ventti not an original
ventti we didn't have that size when we
started that was later on Wow who who
would have thought somebody wanted to
this is America yeah this is
America so my one more question on this
writing the customer's name on the cup
that didn't come from me as the stores
got busier and busier the bries were
having a hard time with whose cup is it
what are we going to do and someone at
Starbucks I don't know who was started
writing names on the cup writing names
and it just became
standard so much of Starbucks success
came from customers asking for things we
weren't doing and Starbucks employees
who became Partners in '
91 understanding the business better
than me and this is all like you know to
my mind just starting to create this
incredible flywheel right if you've got
this 80% gross margin business where the
key lever is repeat loyal customer
visits you've got customization that is
making customers more loyal and
increasing your margin at the same time
because you can charge more for it
you've got the interpers relationship
with the Baristas sure but also even as
you scale I mean the name on the cup
that's something that scales even as
thousands and thousands of people come
into the store the intimacy with the
customer and the Bree became a very
powerful component of the equity of the
experience and I've always thought in so
many ways Starbucks became the first
experiential
brand at
scale we spend any money on marketing
zero there was no money for marketing
and the cup the iconic cup became a
badge of honor because people were doing
something that was new and novel and
walking in the street with it and people
you know what is that there a lot of
that kind of stuff it's your free
billboard yeah that people are proud of
perfect wow well listeners this entire
episode so far we have broadly been
talking about the concept of customer
experience with Howard and we want to
talk about another business that has
been innovating on the customer
experience and that's JP Morgan payments
when it comes to digital Commerce JP
Morgan payments is all about
personalization and convenience both for
consumers and businesses right so on the
consumer side technology has completely
changed expectations for shopping and
commerce whether it's a sneaker drop or
a coffee order customers expect
functionality like ordering in an app
but picking up in store getting
real-time updates and having our
preferences and past orders synced and
remembered yep and importantly we expect
our payments to be simple no matter
where or how we want to pay which
creates real challenges for the business
on the other side of that to create the
magic even with super complex
transactions like a Marketplace website
where you aren't just buying from one
single retailer but a merchant on the
other side of that platform you can
imagine there are plenty of Technical
and Regulatory complexities to make that
frictionless across different countries
and currencies but with with great
embedded finance and Innovative Commerce
Solutions you can Delight customers
without really taking that all on
yourself yep no matter how big or small
your company is you have to manage a
complex technology ecosystem that now
includes online payments inapp payments
social payments inore payments digital
wallets and much more in the future oh
yes like biometric payments which
remarkably research shows that will
reach 3 billion users and $ 5.8 trillion
in value globally by 2026 that is insane
yep and just like Howard pioneered many
firsts in his industry JP Morgan is
doing the same with biometric payments
it's essentially a pay byf face solution
that allows you to complete transactions
seamlessly and securely removing the
need for carrying a wallet or digging
into your bag to pull out your phone
yeah if any of you were at the Formula 1
race in Miami last month you may have
even seen JP Morgan's biometric payments
powering the fast lane checkouts in the
merch store in last Year's pilot
literally every single payment was
processed in under 1 second crazy and
for businesses speed of payments is
obviously great to shorten lines to
quantify that biometric Payment
Solutions have shown to decrease
checkout times by up to 35 seconds per
transaction and increase purchase value
by 4% driving incremental revenue and
maximizing profitability I can totally
attest to this as a customer I basically
only use tap to pay with my watch or
phone everywhere I go now which you know
just felt like sci-fi a few years ago
but unsurprisingly that capability for
merchants to accept contactless payments
is now also being powered by JP Morgan
payments yep so whether you want a full
stack Omni Channel service with
biometric payments or streamlined online
payments with the latest apis JP Morgans
Commerce Solutions work to drive your
business forward with the foundation and
security of a leading global bank and
the innovation of a fintech The Very
Best of Both Worlds that is why we here
at acquired work with JP Morgan you can
check them out JP Morgan / acquired to
learn more and discover more Payment
Solutions powering growth for your
business across every industry from
startups to the Fortune
500 so in this era I mean you must just
be getting more and more excited every
day oh I was out of my mind so David
Howard sent me there's a 1988 I can't
believe this was filmed but a
1988 shareholder and employee meeting
where it's great the whole thing is like
an hour and a half it's it's it's it's
all there and you are using all the same
language that you use today back in 1988
we focus on our people those people
Delight the customer the customer you
know Delights the shareholder or then
satisfies the shareholder and the
conviction that you have it's like
watching a preacher you're up there
you've got I think 11 stores or
something and you're like you have no
idea what we have here we are on top of
something that is going to change and
you don't say the world
America and this thing can become
America's Coffee House MH and it was
interesting because I think the whole
room was already scared of your ambition
of you know going Nationwide with this
thing that there did not exist another
example of a National Coffee House chain
everything was just these little cities
these small markets and there's this
great quote that you have at the end of
the meeting that says the company since
1971 has been growing at a very very
slow pace
as a result of that you combine ilal and
Starbucks together we're going to take
your six stores that you've built in 17
years and we're going to go to 26 in one
year and we're going to go to over a
hundred in five years and that must have
just sounded Bonkers but that is
literally what happened that's what
happened like the pace of growth
approximately you just doubled stores
year over year over year was there some
moment in 88 ' 89 90 where you're just
like looking around
realizing we must expand as fast as we
possibly can because this concept is the
concept the world needs now and if we
don't pull out all the stops someone
else is going to do it there were
Regional competitors who were making
noise about doing what we were aspiring
to do and I was very mindful because one
of them was franchising and that was
Gloria Jeans out of Chicago and at one
point I think they had more stores than
we did because of the franch Fring
opportunity and that's one of the
reasons why I went to Chicago as well in
' 8788 cuz Chicago was the first Market
outside of Seattle and Vancouver right
even before LA and it didn't work right
away huh Howard bear should be credited
with so much of the cultural texture and
the tapestry of the humanity of the
company said I will go to Chicago and
fix it he went to Chicago and stayed in
Chicago through the winter and
re-calibrated the mistakes we were
making and of course he and Orin were so
instrumental
into the loneliness that exists as a
entrepreneur and their ability to help
me build the company that you know today
yeah so I have in my script here this is
literally labeled the uh H2O era and
yeah for anyone who was a partner at
Starbucks sort of knows what I'm talking
about and anybody else outside has no
idea but there's two Howards there's
Howard Schultz and Howard bear and
Howard beard joined in 1989 Orin Smith
joined in 1990 and the way that it looks
to me from the outside and you can tell
me if this is right you were sort of the
vision and ambition that would almost
like take any ambition that anybody else
had and forced them to think bigger and
faster okay and then Howard bear was in
many ways the soul like he brought the
idea of servant leadership he brought
the idea of nothing else matters if we
aren't people first and obviously that
became a huge tenant of Starbucks as we
knew it through the '90s and 2000s but
that seems like it really arrived with
him and then Orin is like a numbers God
no he was the adult in the room more
than the numbers he had the style he was
quiet he was a gentleman he was the only
MBA in the company but he was the wise
man who behind a doors could say to me
and Howard you're both full of
we're not doing that H and we listened
more or
less and is it true that the three of
you had uh dinner every Monday night for
a decade more or less that is true
sometimes more than once if we had a
crisis or two which generally we did or
we had a
disagreement there's a lot of creative
conflict especially between Howard and I
because he had a operate what we were
trying to do and at times he thought we
were growing too fast or head of the
resources
H because he was basically training all
these operators the the the sort of
management Fleet of the company yeah he
was building the operating system for us
to be able to open the store design the
stores which more or less I had done
build them operate them train them and
create the system to handle the flow of
customers so he had his job was much
harder than mine speaking of system what
did your technology look like at this
point oh don't embarrass him no we had
was no there was no
technology no were you running like a
Oracle system not at that time no wow no
we're talking paper yeah it was mostly
manual wow yeah I mean the eventually
when they did get point of sale
terminals they were dos based all the
way through like 2008 right yes yes like
the iPhone was out and you guys had dos
based Point of Sales Systems sounds
right but obviously technology was not
the secret I'm foreshadowing here of the
future of the company yeah so let's take
it forward from this 88 89 90 the first
market after Chicago after you sort of
wred that ship that you decide to enter
on the west coast is La that's the big
fight between Howard and I I don't think
I realize it was a big fight I just felt
in my bones we had to go to to
LA and and he said we're not ready for
La we're going to San Diego I said San
Diego Tri who's in San Diego no we're
not going to San Diego we're going to La
and I've got the location you want to
play in the MJ
yeah so we had a meeting about it and it
it it erupted erupted into
a bad a bad scene and uh one thing led
to another we we did go to La I'm
shocked we did go to La it was fine and
your conviction of we have to go to La
was that for I the equity of the brand I
could see I could Envision the warm
weather and everyone walking around with
our cups and the media and the
celebrities and just the iconic way and
there was nothing in the market nothing
at all that even appeared to be in the
business that we were in and anyone who
was doing it was not doing it well we
had to go and even though we maybe were
not ready we just had to do it and we
did and I think Howard would agree today
that that ended up being a the right
decision and
La the Halo on Starbucks from Seattle
the Vancouver and Chicago was nothing
when we went to LA it just
exploded because celebrities Embrace
Starbucks was there an intentional
strategy to uh create sort of a luxury
brand out of Starbucks that like the
cool people were carrying the Starbucks
cup it might be a little bit expensive
but you can afford it no there was no I
can never remember a
discussion about segmentation of the
brand
because we we wanted Starbucks to be
accessible to all you'd have a CEO of a
company and the person behind them was a
bluecollar truck driver because everyone
could afford the affordable luxury of
Starbucks at the time when you say
affordable luxury what about it was
luxury the quality of the coffee MH The
Experience MH and what it felt like to
walk around with that cup at the
time it was a
badge it was like you were in the
know yeah it wasn't a badge of luxury it
was just like something new so it became
a Trope for decades now that you know
it's oh it's a $6 latte or an $8 latte
or 10 where does that come from in your
mind is Starbucks premium priced is
there actually a Starbucks gets to
charge a little bit more because the
brand has more cache or is that just
completely a farce or myth I think the
pricing of
Starbucks was directly linked to the
economic model that I alluded to
earlier and the rising cost of Labor
rent and the fiduciary responsibility
that we all felt to
achieving the promise we had to our
shareholders and now we're talking about
as a public
company there certainly was a fair
amount of discussion all the time about
the sensitiv ity of the price points and
I think in later years maybe in the last
couple years given the consumer
inflationary time I think it's become a
bit of a of a problem and
certainly I've always said as Starbucks
was growing that the ubiquity of
Starbucks was an enemy to the company
and the challenge was we have to figure
out a way way to ensure the fact that we
are getting smaller as we're getting
bigger and specifically how do we
maintain intimacy and the currency of
trust with our customers and our people
that unto itself is kind of the capsule
of making sure that the growth doesn't
become so intoxicating and so seductive
that we lose sight of the really secret
of the company which was the internal
culture and values which built the brand
and built a relationship with the
customer yeah can you tell us about the
people this is such a huge yeah pillar
to our minds of building Starbucks again
we started this conversation talking
about childhood I really want to build a
different kind of company and and how do
I do that in a way that provides respect
and
dignity because I was so
imprinted with how my my father felt
disrespected valued and kind of vilified
as a
uneducated Blue Collar veteran working
in a series of jobs that he just never
made it and living through the
dysfunction of of a poor family always
under pressure with
money and
so I I wanted to kind of crack the code
on how do we
create benefits that would in a way
uh take the company in Direction no
one's ever been in before and so early
on we started talking about exceeding
the expectations of our people so they
can exceed the expectations of the
customer and the first time we actually
were able to manifest that was a year
before the IPO and and that was an
incredible struggle because I had on my
board two Venture capitalists and I was
proposing something that had never been
done before and that was I wanted to
give equity in a form of stock options
to every single employee in the company
and they just said what what are you
talking about we're not doing that and
so the fight became ultimately we gave
14% of everyone's base pay in the form
of stock options at the end of the year
based on the strike price and I had to
do it the year before the IPO had to so
everyone wouldn't miss it and I think
the the the turning point of the culture
of the company was the day we announced
that and we became partners
and to the credit of Craig Foley who was
the VC and Jamie Shannon they believed
that performance would be enhanced
attrition would be lowered and that the
brand would just Elevate as a result of
that and it was true completely true
that was that that changed Starbucks for
decades and along with some other events
based on doing the right thing I mean
the the healthcare for parttime workers
so then you know Healthcare I think 25
years before the Affordable Care Act
what we did with company for health
insurance and that also I grew up in a
family with no health
insurance and I saw what happened so all
of that is that Argin story of mine of
uh and the tragedy is my father passed
away and never saw what we're able to do
do you want the stats on that initial
Employee Stock Grant I love to hear it
so the program was called beanock
listeners that uh great name Howard was
alluding to amazing name so in 1988 the
uh health benefits roll out even to
part-time employees including gay
couples in domestic Partnerships I
believe the first of its kind that was a
33 store company at that point a few
years later you had grown to 55 stores
you did the LA expansion and then in
1991 which is the year before the IPO
bean stock happens equity in the form of
stock options goes out to everyone
working 20 plus hours a week there were
1,300 employees at the time and uh I
believe it was the first time in history
that part-time employees were offered a
program like this so those initial
grants the strike price was $6 per share
today as we speak the share price is $77
but there have been six splits since
then which comes out to a
64x so that initial Grant has
800x since even the part-time employees
and Bree were offered the opportunity to
buy Starbucks stock yeah a lawyer I
think Scott Greenberg at the time came
to me and said we can't do this unless
we get approval from the SEC because we
were over 500 shareholders so you know
we've studied um lots of amazing
companies on this show who have lots and
lots of different business models but
one thing that just kept striking us as
we were preparing for Starbucks are the
similarities to your neighbor here in
the Northwest in Costco Costco right and
how you treat your people
specifically that's not by accident both
from a uh it's the right thing to do
perspective and the amazing business
model benefit of the retaining employees
I mean it's so expensive to train a new
employee it's not expensive to keep an
existing employee and so you can just
pay people more if you keep them for
longer yeah you know you just basically
have extra money lying around is what
what uh Costco discovered there's so
much about Starbucks to David's Point
that's similar to Costco did you ever
speak with Jeff propman or Jim senagal
or any of those guys about this concept
do you know the answer to that we don't
know assume the answer to this but I
don't know it first Jeff Brockman
invested in Starbucks in the round to
buy Starbucks no way yeah he in that 87
round that's when I met Jeff for the
first time Jeff became a board member of
the early imprinting of starucks
andle clearly a mentor mentor of mine
and then he introduced me to Jim synagog
and so there were many moments of me
sitting with Jeff and Jim including the
huge decision to put Starbucks Coffee in
Costco which there was a Revolt inside
the halls of starucks saying no effing
way wow and we did it and Jeff and Jim
took me to a par paring
lot in Kirkland when I said I don't know
if we can do this I don't know if I can
sell it inside I don't know okay meet us
on a Sunday morning whatever it was look
at the cars these are your
customers in fact putting Starbucks in
Costco we were able to measure directly
the increase in volume in the stores on
the east side as a result of the
proximity to the Costco store you sold
beans we sold beans in Costco and that
brand awareness of I buy Starbucks beans
at home meant that that group of people
went to the stores because we introduced
thousands of Beverage customers to
Costco through the
beans wow so Jeff and Jim were
instrumental in so many things and and
were so kind to me as a young
kid then we went Nationwide with Costco
so this is a thing thing that I think
many people don't realize now that
Starbucks is ubiquitous we sort of
forget about this time when it wasn't
and where people had to find some way to
experience Starbucks you know you only
get a few stores in each of these cities
you're only in a few cities but there
are ways to scale brand awareness and so
you can do things like become the
official coffee of United Airlines or
you know be in uh Costco all over the US
you did this a number of times and I
feel like the rest of the world did not
catch on to what you were doing was just
finding little Billboards everywhere
where you could put the Starbucks logo
and and sort of create that ubiquity
yeah if you thought the Costco Revolt
was high you can imagine when I said we
have an opportunity for United Airlines
people thought that was absolutely
blasphemy don't do that and again the
exposure and the opportunity to surprise
and Delight customers in places that
they' never had anything close to good
coffee all these things when you
consider we didn't spend a dollar a
dollar of marketing dollars ever and so
the the the reputation of the company
was built basically Word of Mouth both
inside our stores and exactly right in
places that we could surprise the
customer and then we also started
putting Starbucks Coffee in grocery
stores which was the other thing because
remember we were building a beverage
business right and we were then going
back to our Core Business in new
channels of distribution it's like the
ultimate goal is to capture those margin
dollars from selling cups of coffees in
the stores that you operate but there's
all these other things you can do that
actually might spit off some profit
dollars but at the very least it's a
break even way to do customer
acquisition and brand building in the
rest of the world I don't know what our
cost of customer acquisition was back
then but it was low well you also you
weren't spending any money on marketing
but United Airlines was paying you for
coffee I assume I don't know exactly how
went down but yeah they're um I have to
assume the Barnes & Noble bar basically
the same thing Barnes & Noble is a
different deal I met Len Rio the founder
of Barnes & Noble very interesting guy
very smart guy great Merchant and we
just started talking he was from
Brooklyn I was from Brooklyn we had a
natural kind of relationship and I said
what do you think about us opening
Starbucks inside Barnes & Noble given
you are the ultimate third place is what
we are and it just again became a
natural extension of our stores we have
a fun uh piece of trivia that you may
know uh related to Costco do you know
where Jeff Bezos and Jim Sagal met for
the first time sounds like in a Costco
not in a Costco in the Starbucks in the
Barnes & Noble in bellw did not know
that and that you know led to so many
things Amazon Prime among them yeah not
know that and I still am friendly with
Jim Sagal today I mean your companies
rhyme in so many ways it's it's uh
that's not surprising at
all I want to talk a little bit um
before we get to the IPO here about what
the strategy was when you expanded
Market by market did you try to sprinkle
a few stores in and see did you try to
move into a market with force and be the
dominant Coffee House chain in that City
uh and in particular it it could be
worth talking about Boston well Boston's
an anomaly because of the acquisition
but bear was so
strident in not expanding to multiple
markets at once and he was 100% right
and so we didn't we went to
Chicago went to LA and we stayed there
for quite a while went to Portland uh we
weren't ready for New York City in terms
of the issues there and but we were very
diligent you went to DC First Years
we were not expanding to multiple
markets until we had enough evidence in
the existing Market that we had success
and we weren't going to compound the
growth in another Market with problems
that we're having in the existing one
and I think that's all be her because he
was he was the managing all the
operations Boston was very different we
had a very strong highquality competitor
called The Coffee Connection in Boston
with a owner operator in George how who
was not unlike Alfred Pete kind of a
gospel of Coffee Culture on the east
coast and we knew Boston was going to be
tough for Starbucks to enter we also had
Dunkin Donuts there like a lot of the
good real estate was taken by the coffee
prodction right yeah and so George and I
never saw eye to eye and but it was
clear that if we came to Boston in a
sign ific way we were going to impact
his business and uh I think to his
credit he was willing to sell so Coffee
Connection was the first acquisition and
we we had to tread very lightly after
the acquisition because of the loyalty
and be careful with the name and and uh
you know solicit George's help and
advice and also we needed him to kind of
validate for us what we were trying to
do and ultimately it ended up being a
very good strategy well it seemed like I
think the numbers are it was uh it's a
little bit after IPO in 94 $23 million
they had 23 locations and they were
doing 16 million a year in Revenue so if
you just look at like the purchase I
think it was onetime sales I think or
maybe a little over one time sales and
the original Starbucks ironically enough
was exactly at onetime sales right
that's what you bought it from the the
founders for if they had the lock on all
the best real estate and they had burned
all the capital figuring out you know
what stores we should be in what stores
we shouldn't be in and then you just get
to like move into that market for
onetime sales you know 1.5 whatever it
is uh with all that already figured out
that's that's pretty amazing it probably
seemed high at the time though I'm sure
it did well isn't that the thing about
valuations and uh they they always it
always seemed like in the good old days
you know everything was undervalued and
yeah okay let's talk about the IPO so it
seems like you knew the moment that you
bought Starbucks from the
founders uh this is going to be a public
company
I thought so there was no I I think it
there
was so much about being a public company
that meant something to me personally
that it validated the company it
validated me my own shame insecurity as
a kid so that was a I was I was a
driving force all along certainly the
the year before with beanock is an
indication what I was planning if
beanock was turned down I I would have I
I would have waited m I just had to that
had to be done I think we only had a
couple of quarters of profitability and
I think we had about 130 stores and what
was the revenue at the time
oh I don't remember exactly I know what
the market cap was the day we went
public I think it you you ended up doing
93 million that year but the the year
before you know was 50 million or
something like that like you companies
went public when they were smaller back
then but well you were a small cap IPO
yeah we were and you know we got turned
down by Goldman Sachs you know that I
did not know that I couldn't believe it
I mean I just I wanted Goldman Sachs as
as the I just you know they were
the the patina on the prospectus to have
Goldman Sachs it would be a very
Starbucks thing for Goldman Sachs to be
the the lead left well uh blank fine I
had a good friend who who was a senior
partner there who since passed away I
thought I had it locked I mean it was
just so many things about it New York
everything thing and they said no you're
too small well the thing that Dan
Levitan told us years ago when we did a
an episode on the Starbucks IPO was that
uh you were really only considering
smaller Banks because it was going to be
a smaller IPO well I was considering it
because gold they told you had no choice
had no choice and Brockman at the time
was not a big fan of wor time schroer
which was Dan levitan's thing and so
Alex Brown became the lead but I also
you know I had my own ego attached to
this I had so much fun on the you know
on the road show I I was just in my
element you know I was looking up I was
trying to figure out you know your
public comps at the time I think there
were zero publicly traded coffee
companies not Bean companies not
retailers not Coffee House chains I mean
truly unheard of so when you're going on
this road show I think people of course
are mystified there's like there's
literally no public companies like yours
you know investor education problem
right yeah I think we had to take them
through everything we had the product
there you know we we served coffee
I you know gave him the whole show we
had a short video that was probably in
black and white the comp always was a
restaurant and I was always fighting
we're not a restaurant we're a hybrid
retailer I never referred to us as a
cafe it was always a store we are a
store we are
Merchants fascinating I mean I go there
and eat many many meals sitting in your
store yeah but as we've been talking
about the economics you were a store we
were a store we were a retail store so
Howard I'm going to take us through the
IPO uh you know you're the first
publicly traded Coffee Company uh you do
end up doing 93 million in in Revenue
that year do you remember the the exact
price IP at yes I me we were we went out
at $17 and the price was 21 the market
cap I think was $250
million can you imagine today a $250
million market cap company going public
and people considering that a success I
mean this is a great at the time for
your employees how crazy is that what 12
18 months before
I guess 12 months before six bucks a
share they tripled their money yeah
fantastic For What and that was when you
started calling them Partners right when
they became 91 as soon as be was
instituted it was everyone was a partner
and is that when you did the lowercase
when titles all became low everyone was
lower case from the beginning oh out of
respect everyone's lower case listeners
when you um when you look up a Starbucks
employee on LinkedIn it always looks
like is that is that a typo and then you
realize there's a pattern all employees
always
put lowercase
titles so another interesting thing
about the uh I was reading the S1 last
night the management team inclusive of
you owned 18% but only 9 to 10% of that
was you personally so the rest of the
management team owned just as much as
you did as the founder yeah that does
feel unusually high do you think that
that played a role in sort of getting
people's buyin and getting them to bleed
Starbucks as much as you did not
intentionally no okay not a strategy no
that was not not a strategy interesting
so then from there you open in
Washington DC on the East Coast I think
that the reason you picked DC was
because your mail order business was
strong there so you sort of had
proprietary data to know that that was
going to be a good coffee City I don't
know how you found that out but that's
accurate in 1995 you cross 500 stores uh
you had just bought the Coffee
Connection as we talked about in Boston
and uh they had one asset that was
perhaps much more valuable than any of
the real estate or any of the uh sales
that you would generate from there they
owned the trademark on the word
Frappuccino and I'm so smart that I
looked at that for frapuccino with
disdain really I didn't like the name I
didn't like the beverage I I didn't
think it was appropriate for Starbucks
and because I just you know I just saw
Starbucks as such a purity with with
regard to coffee
and uh I was wrong dead wrong obviously
putting myself in your shoes back then
now Starbucks and frappucino are like a
it's like a synonym it's like you can't
disentangle them but yeah it's very
different than completely different a
blended cold drink that was the first
cold drink we've ever introduced it was
not a coffee forward beverage when we
introduced it in Southern California was
just it went crazy so what changed your
mind to Greenlight it I didn't have a
choice I mean it it was Coffee
Connection had it then we had it in
Boston people wanted it uh and I just
went along and you you ended up like
reformulating it right it wasn't exactly
the store manager in Santa Monica
reformatted it and she was on it I think
Howard bear loved it people in
California loved it there's a fantastic
story about
Frappuccino because of what we did with
it not in its existing form and Retail
but what we ended up doing with it in
terms of
leveraging the brand and distribution
that's a another great story was that
your first bottled drink in retail yeah
so I went to
Atlanta and Pepsi in the same
day Atlanta being Coke I went to Coke I
went to Pepsi the same day the coke
meeting uh was a meeting lasted less
than 30 minutes I can't can't remember
who I met with they dismissed me uh
didn't view Starbucks at didn't
understand what I was trying to do and
didn't give me much time to even explain
it uh and then I went to Pepsi and this
is 95 is mid 90s 500 stores your public
company yeah but no one but in East
Coast Starbucks wasn't really well known
so I went to Pepsi and purchased New
York Met Roger enrio the iconic CEO and
Craig weatherup the president of of
Pepsi they love the idea and we started
talking about this subsequently Craig
weatherup and I on a napkin I swear
shook hands and created a multi-billion
doll business for Pepsi and Starbucks
and a 50-50 jv on bottle
Frappuccino and Craig weup deserves all
the credit for that and then Craig
became a board member of Starbucks
oh and Roger and I were friends until
his death and served on the DreamWorks
board together how did you find yourself
at Coke and Pepsi pitching a bottled
beverage and was there an internal
Revolt cuz I could imagine people saying
this is a bridge too far I don't think
people knew what I was even doing I mean
I think maybe a few people you know I
just had the thought we got to put this
in a bottle we have to put this in a
bottle and this product if I'm
remembering right was so successful the
instant that it hit sh sore shelves you
had to pull it all off because you
needed to like create new manufacturing
processes and spin up new factories in
order to make enough to actually satisfy
demand basically correct and we also
early on had a recall where they found
glass in the bottle and Pepsi to its
credit took all the blame for that and
fixed it but yeah it was from minute one
the the power of Starbucks and bottle
Frappuccino and doing something we had
never no one it was no bottle of coffee
let alone and uh again just like the
Costco story and the United Airlines
Story the flywheel
of the
awareness and people drinking something
they could enjoy at home or at work
again it just created
another level of velocity on the brand I
mean that I'm just thinking about
between the cups but then United
Airlines and Costco and the cpg products
there's got to have been like 50 billion
Starbucks logos printed I'm sure that
was maybe more maybe more I'm just I'm
sure I could
you can see where the the the the the
size of the equity of the brand was much
bigger than the size of the company much
bigger right because at this point you
like 800 stores yeah then something else
happened and that is we wake up one day
and someone says Starbucks is in a movie
we said what movie You've Got
Mail that wasn't coordinated first of
all Starbucks never paid for place
someone must have approved it I I knew
nothing about it and then someone said
you got to see this movie Starbucks all
over it what movie Tom Hanks You've Got
Mail with Meg Ryan I I didn't know
nothing about it it was just another
thing where it was just like a little
fairy dust on the brand did you know
that it was like the good old days where
you're like this is just like we were so
in the mud it was so in it that we
didn't have a we didn't have time to
look up and we were just running so fast
so hard when you're growing at this pace
it's almost virtually impossible to
catch the growth in terms of the
infrastructure and so you're constantly
back and forth trying to create that
fragile balance between the seductive
nature and the
intoxication of growth and
success and the foundation necessary to
support it and not falling too far
behind where you lose it but you never
are in a position at least we were never
in a position we were we were ahead of
it never and so there was a constant
push and I think this is where Orin was
the wise man in the room to say how
that's we just can't do that now just we
don't have the infrastructure we don't
have the people don't have the systems
and you know I'd be screaming we we we
got to do it if we don't do it someone
else going to do we got to do it and
that takes us International we weren't
ready for that yeah so I want to putting
a bow on Frappuccino the year after it
launched in 1996 Frappuccinos were 7% of
Revenue which I can attest to maybe
freshman is I had my first with that
Frappuccino tall mocha Frappuccino with
whipped cream and a little chocolate
drizzle on top and and like now here I
am drinking what are we drinking here
you're drinking coffee from India yeah
and no cream no
sug and so uh know the the Frappuccino
began my journey to the good stuff uh so
that's the Frappuccino story uh 96 97 98
I mean this is this is the international
story so I love the Japan Story You've
me you've told this to me before but um
I'd love to okay I there's a couple of
things about this I started taking a
couple of
trips uh to Europe and Asia just to get
a sense of what the opportunity would be
and how would we do it I quickly wrote
off Europe because coffee was there I
didn't think we could possibly enter as
an American company and so we just took
Europe coffe be like a uh American
luxury leather goods company coming in
and competing with their Mees yeah not
going to happen and so we said we just
took it off the map and then uh we we
narrowed our Focus very quickly on Japan
Japan had a couple of thousand coffee
stores named doour you'd walk in there
and it was Smoke Filled mostly men dark
but they were successful and so I said
to the board we want to go to
Japan the board was incredibly resistant
to the idea why you've got all this
white space in America there's no need
to do this at the time and I just said
okay well and so one thing led to
another and my board memb said if you're
gonna if you're considering this hire an
outside resource to do a
study oh boy I was livid about that you
know aren't there some Consultants you
could possibly pay to help you know this
uh and so we we hired a consultant who
came back with a you know big book
presented it to the board I had a
preview and it basically was this is a
non-starter you can't possibly succeed
there and in the meeting I was just I
could feel my blood just boiling because
with every statement it was getting
worse like the economics won't
work no one in Japan will ever walk in
the street with a cup of coffee they
would lose face your no smoking policy
which we had from the beginning is a
non-starter and you can't afford the
economics to
rent don't
go well that only made me more Furious
it's like they've never met you and more
intentional and
so we were we kept thinking about this
and then one day we get a handwritten
letter from a Japanese
company and the founder of the company
Eugis son had a la
restaurant and he was enamored with
Starbucks we sit down with him we fall
in love with
him and uh we weren't ready
but we decided we're going to give it a
shot we go to Tokyo we meet him we ended
up forming a JV and you know the folk
law at Starbucks which is not that
unrealistic is the reason we went to
Japan as an international market is
because it had a direct flight to
Seattle that was the extent of our
understanding now we open up in August
if you've been to Tokyo in August it's
hot it's like 95 degree temperature and
100% humidity it's like getting out of a
New York City subway in the middle of
August as soon as you walk out you need
a shower it's going to be a tough
opening because of the hot weather I'm
very concerned about
it I get back to my hotel room and I
have a message that CNN is covering the
opening life
or they got cameras highrisk High reward
wow I'm so nervous at 6:00 a.m. we get
in the car so hot my the tie around my
neck it feels like a a
noose we're driving up to the store in
the Ginza and there's like 200 people
online and I turned to the translator
and I said did he hire
extras I cut the ribbon and a young man
who slept over the night before to be
the first person as a college student
speaks no English He rushes to the front
of the line and I follow him no English
and he says double tall
latte as God as my witness just like
that and I said holy
how did they
know and Japan was a extraordinary
success from minute one we got 2,000
stores there I was there like two months
ago incredible we have a roas right
there why were there people lined up
around the block why did it work so well
instantly was it a strong Co Coffee
Culture or the coffee no it was the
iconic reputation and
anticipation of
something that they had convinced
themselves was unique proprietary not in
Tokyo not in Japan that they wanted to
have and that cup but by the way the
research that cup was all over
Tokyo in months everyone was walking
around with that
cup and this is 9 years after you bought
the six stores it has turned into this
icon in all the events we just covered
Starbucks has already become Starbucks
it is already this like globally
desirable brand there by
1996 I honestly I haven't thought about
it in that way but that's so fast I mean
to build something seem fast to us I bet
the parallels to the Microsoft story are
just like so you know Japan was
Microsoft's First International Market
did not know that it was half their
business and it started in the same way
Bill and Paul got a cold call from K
Nishi who was a guy in Japan who had
somehow gotten a hold of the basic
interpreter loved it and said I'm so
passionate about this I want to bring it
to Japan 50% of Microsoft's revenue for
the first at least 5 years and they
stayed 50% International permanently and
that's what took them right you know
from this Albuquerque to like Hey we're
International all right listeners this
is a great time to talk about one of our
big Partners here in season 14 service
now yes as you know service now is the
AI platform for the Enterprise helping
to automate processes improve Service
delivery and increase efficiency over
85% of the Fortune 500 runs on them and
they have quickly become one of the
world's most important Enterprise
technology vendors today we want to do a
little case study on how service now
works with another very well-known
consumer brand NASCAR little known fact
NASCAR is a family-owned business even
at today's scale in their 75th year
they're continuing to innovate with
events like their race through the
streets of Chicago and growing with over
1,000 NASCAR sanctioned events per year
y the operations are mind-bending I was
looking into it they move a huge part of
the company and set up a new base of
operations in a new City every week the
whole thing is like a roving circus that
needs to build a festival from scratch
while keeping consistent infrastructure
to ensure that fans and teams have a
seamless experience from race to race so
how do you do that well Nascar has
turned to service now to help it become
one of the most Innovative and
technologically advanced organizations
in the sports entertainment industry
with service now they've been able to
automate manual and outdated business
processes and unify fragmented
technology into a single platform
they've also been able to enable their
employees to build low code applications
that can be speedily deployed to all
employees without having big IT projects
associated with it yeah the NASCAR story
is a classic one for service now they
first became a customer for the it
operations but as they saw the power of
the service now platform they extended
it into every corner of their business
from employee experience to app engine
so if you want to learn more about the
service now platform and how it can
turbocharge your business transformation
and the time to to deploy applications
including AI for your business go over
to servicenow.com Acquired and when you
get in touch just tell them Ben and
David sent you so Japan's 96 in 97 you
cross a thousand stores globally you're
getting your feet under you you're
saying okay International is going to be
a thing uh in
1999 you 2,000 stores 2,000 stores
because we had a goal of 2,000 by 2000
We Beat It by Year
ah 99 you also open in Beijing what's
the calculus on entering China and did
you realize it could become such a
pillar of the company like it is today I
I
honestly don't think we had any real
understanding of what we were getting
into and we went there with a partner
that didn't work out we we I should tell
you that we we had a theory of the case
that any International Market that we
opened that didn't speak English we
needed a partner
and so Japan was a partner
successful we entered in a partnership
in China early on that was not
successful did not share our values and
we got out and ended up you closed all
the stores no no we got we got out of
the partnership bought them out and
became company-owned and so you the that
that was legal to do that to be an
American-owned
company in China yeah but we struggled
in China for almost a decade lost money
there was tremendous pressure inside the
company of clothes
China until Belinda
Wang maybe the most valuable person in
the company from my view really yeah
when did Belinda get involved with
Belinda was working she started with
Starbucks in Singapore but she was
working in Hong Kong we were open in
Hong Kong and uh I I saw something in
her who was just an extraordinary
operator and had a touch with people and
I said and we were dying in China we're
really in trouble would you come to
China and run it and she said I would do
I would consider doing
that uh but you've got to decentralize
it and we couldn't do that right away it
was just too much but she changed the
course of history for Starbucks in China
what year was that that she came that
she took over the role I think it's
about a decade after we opened okay well
I I there today I ask because I want to
come back to it there's a whole interim
you know between 2000 and 2008 where you
are not the CEO of the company right so
in 2000 I mean if if if you if you've
been listening to this episode the theme
that should be occurring to you is oh my
God basically everything worked and I
know it didn't feel like that on the
inside but like you read all those
Investment Banking reports and it's like
hey Starbucks uh here's all these price
targets for Starbucks and here's what we
think they're going to do in earnings
and oh they beat it again like I don't
know 30 40 quarters in a row it's just
like this uh I would say perfectly
predictable except you actually kept
exceeding the expectations so it wasn't
predictable I did a 100 quarterly
conference
calls as
CEO
100 yeah that's a lot I bet that's a lot
of earnings prep because each one of
those has what two weeks before it of
the truth is the majority of those were
no
script which became the Le the lawyers
took over after that many years no
script which is your preferred
communication style I mean it seems like
whenever I see you up speaking there's
there's no teleprompters there's it's
from the heart so at this point I don't
want to say it it would be incorrect to
say Starbucks is running itself but like
it's in a great place right and you step
into the role of is it executive
chairman chairman yes executive chair
with Orin as a CEO in 2000 yeah what was
your I was I was I think I was
physically and emotionally
exhausted
um kids were getting older I had missed
a lot just think about all the things we
were doing and I had so much confidence
in or so it was no problem and so that's
what I did but I was still engaged but I
was you know not running it day-to-day
and at this point it's 3500 stores the
company's doing 2.2 billion in Revenue
it kind of feels like okay I can I can
get some distance I can do other things
in life it's it's you know it's going to
work out at some point Orin transitions
the CEO Ro to Jim Donald which I assume
you also very involved in in working
with him um what was that transition
about Orin never wanted to be the
CEO he's not a front
guy uh in fact he's shy and uh did never
wanted to be on the stage as a CEO so he
said I'll do it for a couple of years
but he's always kind of knocking on my
door
saying we we need a new SE H and we
didn't have anyone internally be didn't
want it um and so we did a search we met
Jim Donald great great guy had all this
operational
experience um and then certain things
started appearing and we were just
weren't hitting our stride the way we
usually do the economic environment was
getting tougher and
uh things just kind of unveiled itself
that we it wasn't going to work out
by the way but Jim is a great guy like a
really good person but it just wasn't in
the right fit and so how long had he
been in that role of CEO I'd say less
than three years two years maybe but
basically the um 2008 happens and so the
cataclysmic financial crisis is
unfolding and uh that plus the cracks
that we were
experiencing uh board meeting and I
don't think the board meeting was set up
for me to return but it just kind of
happened in the meeting about okay we
got all these problems what are we going
to do do you want to come back
and yeah I'm going to come back and that
wasn't that was never your intent when
you stepped away you thought you were it
was not my intent to come back it was
certainly not my intent to we're going
to run into problems and so in the
Christmas Vacation of
2007 I knew I was going to return in
January so I was on holiday and I was
starting to think through what I was
going to do on that holiday a friend of
mine not I didn't know he was there but
it was Michael del was there and I must
have talked to him almost every day
about the transformation of Starbucks
and he was going through a similar thing
at Dell almost at the same time so we
had so many things to talk about and we
were comparing notes and
everything and so in early 2008 I spoke
to Jim and I came back in
8 and when you came back in 2008 I mean
this is the whole Crux of your book
onward there's an entire books worth of
material here so we're not going to do
it all but uh suffice to say just to put
some numbers on it um the market cap had
dropped from $30 billion to less than $7
billion same Source sales the the
comparables number when you compare the
store this quarter last year to this
quarter you know or this year to last
year um had dropped growth began to slow
uh and so you come in and you have to
make these really horrible decisions
you're faced with two terrible options
and you got to make the right decisions
for the business I uh first of every
Rock I turned over was worse than I
thought there were a lot of unperformed
stores that should have never been
opened that we need to close I think we
closed a thousand stores and I had a
companywide
meeting I remember it vividly because I
started crying and and apologize to
everybody that we got to close stores we
got to lay people off and I mean just
think about you know we were on a a
trajectory for all this time and all of
a sudden we not only hit a speed bump
but the world the music was just
stopping the stock price I think broke
$6 I was so afraid that we were going to
get acquired but the only cover we had
is that the world was coming undone so
no one had any resources but I was
terrified I just stood up and apologized
and said we we we've let you down I
promise I'm do my best but we're trying
to save the company and literally we
were trying to save Starbucks things
were that bad you say that we were
trying to save Starbucks and in my head
I always thought well it couldn't have
been that bad this is big successful
company it's fast growing it's
profitable and then I read you were
seven months from being insolvent so we
had uh we didn't have enough cash comps
had we never had negative comps in the
history of Starbucks so negative I
didn't single quarter was better than 12
mon never had never had a negative comp
month in my history of of the company I
didn't even understand how it I
understand it such an
anomaly
so um we we close all those
stores and um then you got to decide
okay how do we how do we turn it what
what do we do and I think going back to
your line of questions in the past about
the people is of all the things things
that I could point
to that demonstrates what Starbucks is
has been and needs to be it's the
humanity and the people of the company
the company was
built
on being a performance-driven company
through the lens of humanity that's how
it was built and whenever we've lost our
way we've lost our way because people in
power didn't understand
understand that
equation and so I I just said we need I
I need to be in front of every store
manager I need a meeting with 10,000
people it's the big conference room and
so in
2008 no American company was
traveling and so the municipalities were
hungry for Starbucks to potentially have
a meeting at a
discount and so we got we had Detroit
come in we had Houston come in and then
New Orleans came in what they presented
to us was the need for Starbucks to come
as a result of
Katrina and when we heard that we
realized we've got to go to New Orleans
and in fact what we're going to do in
New Orleans is we're going to have one
full day of 50,000 hours of community
service in the ninth ward next day we we
walked through and we built basically a
tutorial
on how to restore the business and have
people walk through it and we had
classes and we had all these things
going on and the third day was my speech
in the basketball Coliseum to 10,000
people I'm about an hour before I was
really feeling the burden of how
important what I was going to say is and
the CFO at the time who subsequently
resigned a week later wasn't my
guy asked me what I'm going to
say and I said I'm going to tell him the
truth and he says you can't possibly do
that you're going to scare the out
of them I went up there and I laid it
out chapter and
verse I think we have seven months
left we are going to be
insolvent I can see why he was freaked
out about this like if word got out to
Wall Street that yeah well social media
didn't exist that time but I just laid
it out what if that store was the
difference between the food on your
table and its success and then I had
this economic formula of how many
customers it would take per store to
turn comps around and the number was low
it's like less than 10 per day or 11 per
day H and so I said let's just talk
about New Orleans you know how many new
incremental customers it'll take in your
store and it's ma was manageable and
tangible mhm anyway right because you
could actually imagine okay if 10 more
people walk in the door today and I
Delight them in a particular way that
brings them back tomorrow like we're
turning this thing around or we're
turning this one store around and if
everybody does that yeah and and the
problem when you get this big is you
start thinking about large numbers but
if you reduce it to the lowest lowest
common denominator one store one cup of
coffee One customer one partner and what
if all of that works well we rushed out
of New Orleans like an effing tidal wave
and we never looked back and less than a
year was turned and you you did crazy I
mean the the tactics involved in the
turnaround the we close the stores for
what noon onward right for an entire
afternoon an evening because the
previous
administration had done things that
diluted the Integrity of coffee to
maximine
yield like what what does that mean well
let's say you're making a batch of brw
coffee yep well what if that brw coffee
was based on a number of ounces of
coffee what if you just reduced it just
a little bit no one's going to
know just little things little little
10,000 little sounds good in theory
scratches of efficiency that dilute The
Experience yeah huh but that does seem
like a reflects a misunderstanding of
the fundamental business that this is a
business about a store with high gross
margins based on Customer
Loyalty but we were beginning to face
headwinds MH and what are the headwinds
headwinds were the level of attrition of
customers as the financial climate
deteriorated spending that $6 on the
latte
daily get hard to justify and we weren't
as good as we we were when we were small
yeah then it makes it easier to give up
yeah and this goes back to what I said
earlier growth covers up mistakes and
success breeds yubis and it did how
could it not I mean how how could you
Starbucks today is so freaking
ubiquitous which again is one of the
things I love about it it's consistent
anywhere I travel in the world I can
count on it I can mobile order and pay
there's all these wonderful things but
when you become like government level
scale in the world people assume it's a
piece of public infrastructure I assume
employees even must feel that way during
some periods of time of like we're so
big we're just but the the worst thing
that Starbucks could have become and the
worst thing that Starbucks could become
is a
utility scale and ubiquity creates
complexity complexity demands
efficiency but we are in a business
where
that touch point between the customer
and the Barista has to be
protected and has to be elevated now
then you get stores that are so busy
where the Barista can't even look up
can't look up and then you get mobile UD
and pay which we haven't even talked
about which is you know is a thing I
love and do every day and depersonalizes
the experience by definition yes
Starbucks demands nurturance it's it's a
a company that has to be nurtured like a
young child that is an anomaly
inconsistent with scale and you get
people coming into the company with
different experience different
language the immersion doesn't quite hit
them in the heart or the soul or the
conscience of the company they they feel
like they're doing a good job but it's
not the job that's consistent with the
integrity and
Heritage of what the company has been
metaphorically let's let's say that's a
giant Reservoir if you're taking a
deposit on a consistent basis out of the
reservoir and it's getting dry you
better stop you better make sure you're
making a deposit so they're equal and
it's balanced when you get
this that's when the company loses the
plot and if you get this and you're
making a lot of money and the stock
price is high people say it's okay we're
fine and that's Fool's Gold it's it's a
camouflage because eventually it's going
to bite you in the ass have you ever
figured out a way to measure these
things in a way that like as long as
these numbers that that the numbers are
a direct tie to our values are good we
can actually put a kpi against them we
know that the core is solid I I haven't
been smart enough to figure that out but
I mean I think the interesting thing to
me today is that the Asian business
is operating at a much higher
level of the soft side of
Starbucks than we are in the
US and I now I understand your Belinda
Wong comment that doesn't answer your
question about quantifying it but when I
am in Asia I see things that
are very elevated to the brand that
speak to the financial performance of
those markets which are very high okay
before we get to today I want to talk
about some other things that happened in
2008 2008 was a big year so 2008 2009
2010 there's no way to put it other than
a wildly successful turnaround your low
point in 2008 profits were 315 million
and by 2010 they were 945 million I mean
I don't know how we did that well we
just went through a lot of the ways of
how you did that there's a couple other
things here one of which is technology
but I'm told there's a a story you have
about Steve Jobs
around this point in time too funny
story another story and
so in Hawaii when I was on vacation I'm
talking to Michael Dell and Benny off
and you're uh cycling with cycling with
Dell almost every day and I'm talking to
Benny Michael introduced me to Benny
didn't know
him and
so his a pretty good Hawaii crew okay so
I get back and um Adam brotman was a key
person in all this in terms of mobile
order and pay yeah he ran digital for
Starbucks yeah he ran digital I'm trying
to make sure I got the sequencing of
this right I think there was
a future meeting scheduled for Starbucks
and
apple uh
around mobile order and pay and other
things and I met Steve on a phone
call I never met him talking to him on
the phone and I I'm telling him what's
going on he said you should come down
and he had a whole thing about walking
he would go out we'd walk around the
building you heard this before infinite
loop at their old campus yeah yeah yeah
and so I went down there and and
basically went down and we took a walk
and I just told him all my problems
everything was going on and he just
stopped me and he said this is what you
need to do this looked me and he said
you go back to Seattle and you fire
everyone on your leadership team I
thought he was joking I said what do you
mean fire what are you talking about
fire everybody he said I just told you e
and fire all those people he's like
screaming at me in my face you know fire
all those people that's what I would do
I said Steve I can't fire all the people
who's going to do the work he said I
promise you in six months maybe nine
they'll all be
gone he was right except for one The
General Counsel they were all gone your
whole leadership team turned over after
they were all
gone wow that's story about stew jobs
wow did you ever call him back and tell
him I talked to him since then and we
were on stage together at an event and I
told them they're they're all gone well
you're 6 months nine months late man
think about all the things you could
have done of
course all right that's that story so
while we're in technology land then
um I think today
33% of Starbucks orders are done with
mobile order and pay so obviously this
you know huge pillar of of Starbucks as
it exists in our world how did that
start yeah yeah you had been on pen and
paper then you moved to dos and now you
have the most sophisticated technology
platform of probably any retailer in
World at the time so you're talking to a
non-te person so I'm not I'm not focused
on anything other than the customer
experience y uh Adam Brockman to his
credit along with Steven Gillette who's
who was at Starbucks very shortly
came to us with the idea of building a
mobile
app I didn't know what it was what do
you honestly we're in the meeting I'm
trying to figure out what what are you
actually talking about how are they
going to do that they created and apps
at this point I mean if it came out in
2009 which was the first version the iOS
SDK came out in summer 2008 summer 2008
so it's like you know you're one of the
very if they're having this idea and
bringing it to you it's like months
after
exist well they're they get complete
credit
for assembling the pieces of all
this convincing us to fund it and we
were off and running I don't think any
of us honestly for myself really knew
what they were actually going to create
they explained it to us but I didn't
really I didn't get it until I saw it
and holy overnight it was just an
unbelievable new
vehicle now if we fast forward I don't
know if you want to do that here of what
it's become yeah it
is the biggest Achilles heel for
Starbucks really and it's not even a
close
second and
so the mobile
app created unbelievable
convenience for our customers but
remember we are an
experiential
brand and so as this thing was
growing there was never an
opportunity because it it it it became
so seductive for the
company it also created a even better
business model for you right it was more
efficient and you get the float with
yeah with all that is true but at but it
was beginning to deteriorate yeah at a
rapid rate the the third place
experience in the sense of
community and then it became it
overflowed to the point where it
disproportionately created an
environment in our stores where the
mobile app became the primary
vehicle as well as the primary vehicle
for dissatisfaction
because people couldn't get their drink
on time people were confused whether
that was their drink a lot of anxiety
and the thing I remember the most is
that we were in Chicago at 8:00 a.m.
because people wanted to show me the
problem and so everyone is getting off
the loop the train at 8:00 a.m. and
everyone who ordered on their app it
says the same thing your drink's going
to be ready in seven minutes and
everyone shows up and all of a sudden we
got a mosh
pit and that's not
Starbucks and so the
company did not do a good job of
anticipating the technological
refinements that needed to be put in
place to avoid what was
happening and I want to be fair to
everyone who's managed the company for
about a five-year period remember I
haven't I wasn't involved in the company
from basically
2018 to
2022 yep not I wasn't I was not involved
you stayed CEO from 2008 until
2017 then I left and
um there were no bad people and no one
had bad
intentions but the Heritage and
tradition of what I've described which
is so vital to the nurturance was lost
well it must have been so seductive yeah
the stock we the stock was at record
High and the company was not
investing ahead of the curve and not
paying attention to the velocity of the
mobile app and what it was becoming
until it was too late and now and the
company has that problem today which
they will solve but it's it's late and
also everyone has caught up to we we
were the only game in town and and the
novelty of that and the uniqueness of it
especially for our product MH and
everyone
pretty much copied it it is interesting
to David keeps saying it's so seductive
to put some numbers for listeners
wondering you know why is the mobile app
such an interesting thing David pointed
out the float so of course uh if you
look at Starbucks uh financial
statements right now at any given time
there's about $1.8 billion doar of cash
that Starbucks has gotten in the form
effectively of as an advance from
customers that Starbucks can use to
operate it's like this amazing growth
Capital you know store expansion etc etc
right not the only one I mean everyone
right you know the Amazon has this Apple
has this brire has this the insurance
business but it's effectively interest
free loan from customers and a loan
that's not all going to get called at
once it's uh some of it will never get
called right the the breakage and so
there's this benefit of like it's a
reasonably predictable amount of cash
that comes in that you get to use um you
know for your advantage uh in terms of
velocity
about4 billion a year gets loaded onto
gift cards that's unbelievable I mean
that if you actually like look at all of
the banks in America if Starbucks were a
bank and you treated the gift cards as
deposits it would be in the top 10% by
deposits of banks in the United States
it's this like unbelievable business
model that happens to exist inside of
this experiential business that powers
this experiential business but to your
point you have to keep it from eating
the core yeah so let's just go back not
to the economics but the the idea itself
and I think whether we talked about
bottle
Frappuccino the cup you just thread all
these things there is there is a common
through line and that is we took a
commodity
business and we transformed it into a
premium product brand and experience
but when you are disrupting the
market there has to be some governor on
the on the disruptive innovation to
monitor how is it being used how is it
being abused and the era of judgment in
the period where this was really kind
of uh where we really took hold this
fiveyear period between 2018 and 2022
it's a governor didn't exist oh you feel
like it wasn't really taking hold in
that whole it was taking before you know
and and I'm not criticizing anyone
because you know we're all everyone's
trying to do a good job but the the the
result is the the the runner the The
Unbelievable
success it disrupted The Experience yeah
and now you have stores that are
entirely built to just pick up mobile
orders and so and and my view is we
should not succumb to the mobile app
looking back now and not when you're in
the moment and you and others in the
management team things happen but
knowing what you know now yeah are there
a couple key design decisions or things
that you would re architect differently
about the mobile app experience I I
don't think I would have allowed the
mobile
app to be on demand 24 hours a
day h i I would have slowed rolled the
the
availability of it and then understood
how it was being used and whe and
whether or not it was going to disrupt
the experience but now it's it's you
know on demand whenever you want it
right and now you can't you can't shut
it off from
8 whenever I get that that message um
you know mobile Order ahead is not
available at this time I'm like H but
it's available 99% of the time it's not
available now and because the store I
won't even go to a store if it doesn't
have the store's overun you wouldn't go
yeah that breaks my heart I hate that
hate to hear
that well there I went to the precidio
store yesterday in San Francisco and I
would go there no matter what but if you
know I only agree with you in airports
in airports I'm so time constrained that
I'm like if mobile order isn't working
the line's too long oh but I've had
plenty of times where like I'm looking
at stores in the radius I'm in I'm
traveling I'm in a new city and it's
like well I'm only going to go to the
one that's open for mobile order and pay
I'm not even going to try I got to hit
one other Howard I know you hate it but
one other like amazing business model
benefit of mobile order and pay if I'm
buying $6 lattes over and over again
with my Visa card and Starbucks is
getting hit with 30 cents every time
instead if I'm buying $25 gift cards
well that's now three out of four times
I'm I'm going and buying my coffee and
Starbucks doesn't have to pay Visa 30
cents or the bank 30 cents that's a
pretty amazing business unlock like you
know I'm I I'm aware it degrades The
Experience so you have to find ways to
deal with that but I I'd be more than
willing to sacrifice economics to go
back to ways to enhance the experience
myself but I'm not unch
charge all right listeners this is the
perfect time to talk about another one
of our favorite companies and longtime
acquired partners pilot.com for startups
and growth companies of all kinds pilot
handles all of your company's accounting
tax and book keeping needs and in fact
now is by far the largest startup
focused accounting firm in the entire us
we talk all the time on acquired about
Jeff bezos's AWS inspired Axiom that
startups should focus on what makes your
beer taste better in other words only
spend your limited time and resources
only on what's actually going to move
the needle for your product and
customers and Outsource everything else
that you need to do as a company but
doesn't fit that bill yeah while we're
in beverage land Starbucks is actually
great example of this there are so many
things that are not proprietary to
Starbucks for the most part they don't
own the real estate that the stores are
in they don't manufacture the bottle
beverages like Frappuccinos that you see
in grocery stores they use Pepsi for
that and they don't make their own cups
napkins silverware any of that from
scratch they focus on what makes their
coffee taste better I love that for
startups and growth stage companies
accounting is example number one of this
idea every company needs it it needs to
be done by a professional and you don't
want to take any risk of something going
wrong but at the same time it has zero
impact on your actual product or
customers so enter pilot pilot both sets
up and operates your entire company's
Financial stack so Finance accounting
tax and even CFO services like investor
reporting from your general ledger all
the way up to budget and financial
sections of your board decks and they've
been doing this now for years across
thousands of startups from Silicon
Valley and everywhere else so there's
really no one better that you can trust
to both get your Finance right and make
it easy and painless for your company
yep and when you say thousands of
companies pilot does this for these are
now companies like open AI air table and
scale as well as large e-commerce and
other companies so it's not just that
they have experience across startups
they can also keep working with you as
you scale to the growth phase and Beyond
so if your company or a company you
start in the future wants to go back to
focusing on what makes your beer or
coffee taste better go on over to
pilot.com
Acquired and tell them that Ben and
David sent you thanks pilot moving on
from technology and mobile order and pay
there's one more to my mind key pillar
of the Starbucks tapestry and that's
real estate and maybe this is a good
time because I feel like around this era
is when people started looking at
Starbucks and scratching their heads and
being like there's two Starbucks across
the corner from one another these guys
must be insane uh talk to us about real
estate
uh the the basic idea early
on uh given the beverages velocity in
am uh was to find a corner location in
an urban setting where we could
physically see pedestrian traffic in a
significant way and so we would go to
cities and
count just physically account how many
people were walking by what hours they
walking by and once we had a model of
success it became clear to us what we
needed and also once we became aware of
co- tencies of certain tenants that
would be interesting to us um we also
were very intrigued with being next to a
grocery store early on because of the
frequency in which people were buying
food anytime were in an office building
where there was 3 to 4 th000 people in a
building that was a home run but then it
became very clear that there were
locations that we never imagined we
could be in that became wildly
successful and just opened up an
aperture to us that
basically we had opportunities to do
things that were not traditional for a
retailer now the other thing which we
haven't talked about is the decision I
made early on not the franchise which
you haven't surprised you haven't
mentioned that oh well there were
franchises but I'll let me explain that
if I can which is all part of the real
estate strategy I I never
believed that we
could build
maintain and Elevate the culture of the
company which I viewed as the thing in a
franchise system where we had individual
franchisees who had their own subculture
and so even though there was pressure
early on because of the cost of capital
and we didn't have a lot of money to
franchise we'd have no capex I said no
we resisted that and I don't think we'd
be having this conversation if Starbucks
was a franchise system because
McDonald's extraordinary company but
they're they're a commodity-based
product what was he been saying it's
from the beginning it was about
elevating yeah McDonald's great company
but nobody would ever accuse them of
elevating I don't think yeah and that's
why I I I don't want Starbucks to become
transactional coffee is
personal the biggest magic and what you
know the lightning in the bottle is when
you go to Japan or Shanghai or Malaysia
and you see the
culture in a way that you just can't
believe like how did it happen that we
were able to transfer this to another
country different language different
culture different how do we do it that's
actually quite befuddling to me cuz so
many food and beverage Concepts do not
transfer geographies and and I think it
transferred
because young people around the world we
all want the same
thing they want opportunity they want to
be respected they want to be rep they
want they want dignity they want to make
their parents proud they want to work
for a company that they believe in and
when I see what we've done around the
world I'm moved emotionally because the
humanity I speak of is universal that's
why when I came back from China what I
said was I just want to say something
about China and the US I know all the
rhetoric and the propaganda about our
two countries but what I see is that we
have so much more in common than we have
differences and that should be the theme
of the world right
now I want to pick up the thread on
China now that we're of into the 2010s
okay this decade saw huge ridiculous
growth in China store openings so there
were 500 stores in 2011 right when
you're sort of coming out of that the
the rut by 2017 there were 3,000 today
there's almost 7,000 and there was a
stat that was reported that a new store
opened in China every 15 hours in 2017
true now bring us to that seed that you
planted earlier with Belinda being the
single most important
employee China
presented the enormity of
opportunity with the significant
challenge of
pioneering and it's a tea drinking
culture yeah tea drinking culture no
morning business people eating rice in
the morning we got real estate wrong we
got breakfast wrong but it was all
coming from the control of
Seattle did you go in with essentially
the Starbucks concept yeah was exactly
what you see right now there's no no
different but they didn't know the
Chinese people hardly knew what coffee
was there was no morning
traffic and in the early days of our
partner we we didn't see eye to eye so
we got them out when Belinda came along
we had a worldclass operator who had
succeeded in Singapore and Hong Kong
she's a strong person who believed that
Seattle the way we were organized was
not a formula for Success you can't have
people in Starbucks in Seattle designing
the breakfast menu who have never been
to China who think we're they're going
to eat blueberry muffins and so when she
said to me I will do
it if I'm in control of everything so I
want to decentralize
China I report to you it's you and me
and John Culver who runs International
take Seattle out of the
equation we were failing what choice did
I have H she turned it she
singlehandedly built the China business
today 18% of Starbucks's revenue is
China yeah she deserves all the
credit John and I have been to China
almost every quarter during the building
years of turning it with her and all the
government me meetings to tell the
Starbucks story and and then we did
things in China
disruptively well Belinda decided that
she could go to the government and go to
an insurance company and come back to
Starbucks and get government approval
for Starbucks to do the F do something
had never been done before and provide
health insurance to the parents and
grandparents of our
partners cool so
the Chinese government was so intrigued
sitting down with them saying can you
can you explain why do you want to do
this right you don't have to yeah right
yeah because it's the culture of our
company we we want to do everything we
can to benefit our people humanity and
it's
Universal but it's so I think important
to
just um create at some guard
rails
so one day in the early stages of
Starbucks Howard beer comes to my office
one day remember we're small at this
stage and he says we we got a terrible
situation
said the manager of the Seattle trust
store on second in Madison Seattle Tom
carrian has
AIDS now AIDS at that time time was like
leprosy
leprosy so he Tom comes
in and he says I need to resign from
Starbucks and he's
crying do you have any health
insurance
no and so we covered Tom carrian from
that point on but it was those kinds of
imprinting moments and there were many
like that right I think it's funny so I
have
heard that story probably five times
because I've consumed an incredible
amount of Starbucks content over the
last couple months and I've heard a a
story about
uh Starbucks employees wanting to buy a
cow for a farmer in Africa and stories
about Flint Michigan and stories about
get the initiative to bring the company
together to try to bring the country
together when the government was shut
down in 2013 whenever that was and I I I
was getting frustrated watching all
these stories because I kept thinking
this is not the answer to why Starbucks
worked these are these one-off anecdotes
that are sure they're emblematic of some
broader theme but at the end of the day
like the answer to why Starbucks Works
has to be something about the business
model and every time you walk into the
store XYZ happens and here's the
economics but it turns out there are
thousands of these stories and it's the
humanity seeping through and it's hard
for the company to tell the story
because everyone just feels like a
random oneoff example but they're
happening in every community in every
part of the country and I think that is
the for me as like a business historian
that's been the thing that jumps out is
there's no other company that we've
studied that has this sort of obsession
with people and Humanity the way that
that Starbucks does and we're not
perfect and so we do make mistakes and
when you're when the brand is being
shined so brightly it's a high standard
to be held to we live in an environment
where if you do make a mistake and we
are human we're going to make mistakes
unfortunately that becomes the thing yep
uh and it's tough to fight that are you
open I'd love to kind of Flash Forward
uh you know you were CEO through 2017
Kevin Johnson took over 2017 to 2022 you
came back for one year as interim CEO
and now laxman is the the CEO and has
been in the seat for about a year
um you came in after a tumultuous Co era
and and tried to basically figure out
who the successor was going to be and
and you know patch the ship in the
meantime a lot of stuff has has happened
in that last five years notably with
labor unions I don't want to make this a
podcast about labor unions but I do want
to ask you what have you learned from
the experience of you know having to do
a deep dive into how we got
here that's a very tough comp comp Lex
question
uh I
think
my personal
relationship with the company and
how personal it is to me and the things
that we not I but we have tried to do to
build a different kind of
company uh when the country started
moving in a postco era to a direction
that I didn't
recognize very very hard to
understand why Starbucks would be under
assault or
or just being challenged this
way particularly when you had built a
reputation on a very pattern in a
history of being
unbelievably kind to your people yes
yeah I
entered Starbucks as the interim CEO
when this was already going on and I
think the company made some early
mistakes some of which were covid
related again no textbook had to deal
with covid issues health issues safety
issues uh and then I think uh
underestimated the ground swell
of public
sentiment uh for this movement in
America and
um then became vilified for trying to
defend the company in a way that I
thought was
appropriate um I think what's lost in
all this is the percentage of stores
that have been petitioned and the number
of people is very small in relationship
to the to the whole and then all of the
people in Starbucks who were depending
on me to defend the company and trying
to do that in a world of disinformation
is very difficult at the time when I was
trying to restore the company back to
health clearly mistakes were made this
story is still
unfolding and um my heart's with the
company and but the thing that I think
was lost in the story is the shareholder
is not the primary person it's the
Starbucks partner in the green apron
which is the cloth of the company and if
we exceed the expectations of the cloth
of the company and our people
shareholders and customers are going to
win that's been my whole life story and
that's basically worked for decades and
decades it also seems like when you
Starbucks has become such an institution
in our society that leading a small
disruptive
organization everyone gives you the
credit for all the positives and all the
exciting things you're doing and you
sort of get a pass on anything that
didn't work move F break things when
you're at this scale everyone expects
you to be wildly successful all the time
because you always have been but
anything that's misaligned that is where
100% of the focus
is well I think if you take a step back
not from Starbucks but if you say to
yourself what company has gotten big in
the food business and stayed true to its
core purpose and reason for being and
then stayed positively
inclined to its
customers what are you going to name and
so the odds on getting this big and
still being revered for who you once
were is very very difficult and I would
argue in so many ways we are better
today than we were when we were smaller
that is expected of
us uh but I don't think we get much
credit maybe we shouldn't maybe this is
uh our
responsibility the elements the
characteristics that built the Starbucks
business the culture is compassion
empathy and love those are not just
words it's like real things that are not
they're not being taught in Business
Schools and people on the outside view
it is not true I'm telling you the
reason we've succeeded is because the
underpinning of the company's purpose
has been just that and it's much harder
today to to execute that because you're
you're dealing with cynicism as the
first order of defense that you have to
overcome but the
responsibility as Leaders is to do just
that all right I'm going to take us to
Starbucks today and I'll kind of map
that out and give you the stats and then
we're going to go into Playbook where we
basically try to take all the lessons we
just learned over the last few hours and
figure out why did Starbucks work um and
at such a grand scale that it did so to
catch listeners up on the business today
Starbucks does 36 billion in Revenue 4.1
billion in net income there are 380,000
employees you gave me a stat I think
over 4 450,000 450,000 I must be using
an old number um and over the lifetime
of the company has employed over 5
million yes 5 million alone that a scale
right there 39,000 stores globally in 86
countries almost half of which are in
North America 18% in China and uh about
half of those are licensed franchise and
half are company operated and so while
we're not you know you you mentioned we
don't franchise in the traditional
McDonald's sense you do these joint
ventures and you do this uh this way of
entering countries where you don't need
to own and operate the entire store
yourself then not franchises in the ipal
sense yeah so tell us about I think we
should talk about that yeah the joint
venture relationships that we've
established and some goes back almost 30
years in the Middle
East in Latin and Central America now in
Italy in the
EU in
India and what does it mean to be your
partner so uh every country is different
depending on the economics of that
country the political
issues um some countries have been an
8020 Starbucks owns 80 they own 20 some
are 5050 some are some of the 8020
started out as 80 for us and they bought
it in over the way uh it depends so but
the the key thing is whether it's
Alberto torado Latin and Central America
Muhammad alai in the Middle East the
Tata group in India the prasi family in
in in Italy they understand the culture
and values of Starbucks
and so
tactically what you know you said it's
not a franchise in the traditional way
what are Starbucks responsible for and
what is the partner responsible for
Starbucks is responsible for roasting
the coffee MH for all the recipes which
are consistent with Starbucks
worldwide a co-design to the store where
we're designing the store with the JV or
the licensed partner and they control
all the operations h and so all of
Starbucks's franchise or license stores
are done in this way where there's a
partner in a country yes that there not
no individual licens franchises of any
kind unless it's certain real estate
that we can't get uh that we want access
to like the a roadway uh on a highway in
Switzerland or something odd see and
airports are this way right airports are
Master licensed with the with the master
licy like Whoever has it in like
Marriott or whoever has it I gotcha or
Target that has 2,000 Starbucks stores
and those are Target Opera yes I see and
great partner and Brian Cornell great
guy and it's interesting the basically
you know half of Starbucks stores look
like the platonic ideal of coming out of
the Starbucks HQ here's how we imagine
this this store to be and half of them
are there's some reason why we alone
can't do this and need a partner and you
you know
you I mean ideally want the customer
experience to be the same worldwide
regardless of the shape and size of the
store where it's located makes sense
which is not always the case I I admit
that so one market that we haven't
talked about that I I want to ask you
about while we're in this then we'll get
to Playbook is Italy yeah the whole
thing came out of Milan right and yet
for decades 50 years no Starbucks 50
years no no Starbucks in Italy and the
belief at least as I see it is they've
perfected the coffee house concept don't
bring an imitation in
here yeah but it's worked it's it's
working phenomenally well why is
Starbucks being so well-received in
Italy so I I know I'm going to
be chastised for what I'm about to say
but it's
true the by and large coffee in Italy is
not as good as it once
was there are certain coffee companies
that have maintained the standard but by
and large the coffee is not as good I'm
going to be killed for that but that's
that's that's my truth if you don't
believe you have a better product who
does yeah but I I didn't think we earned
the right to go to Italy until we were
really ready to present ourselves in the
best possible way because I knew the
knives would be out for us and ways that
we could couldn't even possibly imagine
given the the history and the cultural
relevance of espresso in the coffee bar
and so we waited and waited and waited
until The
Roastery and so I before we get to Italy
I have to explain The Roastery for you
please I mean the first time I went in
there you know kidney candy store wide
eyes so there are six roasteries
starting in Seattle Chicago New York
Tokyo Shanghai and Milan the road
Roastery itself is probably the most
entrepreneurial creative
project that I could recall in my
history of
Starbucks what is the experience we
could create that just absolutely blows
people away so what did I
do as a kid I've Loved this
movie and so I invited the most creative
people in the company to my house and I
said we're going to watch a movie
of course they thought I was nuts and I
turn on Willie Wonka I was say got to be
turn on Wily W Wonka with Gene
Wilder and we went to work starting to
design a
space now we realized early on and this
was what
2013 eight years ago now we realized
economically this is a tough business
model so what are we trying to do we're
trying to create an experience that is a
to the brand and significantly elevat
Starbucks which is fighting ubiquity all
the time every day and
so we created this 30,000 foot space in
Seattle which we opened seven years ago
which is the most
dynamic
entertaining vehicle of theater romance
seduction and we open it to rave reviews
and we're manufact facturing like Willie
Wonka did were manufacturing and
roasting coffee in the space which makes
the smell of
the so we open it up and then over time
we started opening a couple more we get
approval from the Chinese government to
manufacturer in the center of Shanghai
we open up a 40,000 foot in Shanghai we
open up an incredible space in Tokyo we
open up in the old Craton Barrel space
in North Michigan Avenue in
Chicago we open up in the me packing
business in New York but the
shrine has to be Milan this is the way
to go back and this is the way we open
on Italy
now our partner in Italy is the prasi
family fantastic people who are in the
real estate business and they are
showing me I'm going back and forth to
Milan like all the time because they've
got real estate and I got to see it I
got to touch it I got to smell it I keep
going back and back and back no not the
right sight not the right sight and I'm
standing
on the corner of of cardo square and I
look at this face and I say what about
that and he says that's the post office
you can't get the post I said well it's
empty it's empty you can't get it so I
said can I meet the landlord said Howard
it's the
government I said well who who Who's
responsible for it so they arrang a
meeting for me and I meet the broker
Who's involved in this but it's it's
empty
space and find out the story is that
these government buildings during the
financial crisis were sold to private
Equity so I said who's the
landlord I'm not I can't tell you said
you have to tell me who the landlord is
private Equity that's letting real
estate sit
empty where this is going okay it turns
out I know I'm going to get killed for
the story you're gonna have to fix
this turns out the owner of the space is
Blackstone no I knew it I knew it of
course of course so I said why am I in
Italy I called John yor called John Gray
up no way I said John I'm in Milan do
you realize you own this space in cardo
square that used to be a post office he
said I don't know let me check you know
said John I'm coming to see you
tomorrow I'm on the next flate we do the
deal with John Gray amazing unbelievable
we John Gray of course being the number
two person at Blackstone so uh and
John's a big fan of Starbucks he had
previously been in Seattle for a wedding
or bar mitzvah something and saw The
Roastery he knew exactly what I was
talking about and so that is how we
entered in Milan now we have 30 stores
we have 30 traditional stores in Italy
did they already exist before the roas
open open first first the roas then 30
stores in we're in Milan we're in Rome
and we're in Florence and um
two three years
later what do you think the number one
beverage
is it's
espresso for Starbucks yeah straight
espresso espresso is the number one
beverage wow wow and so we're I don't
take the the success in Italy for
granted we've got to continue to earn it
but what I'm most proud of is that we've
respected the Italian people and Coffee
Culture for 50 years and they they
embraced us and so the implication of
espresso being the number one beverage
is it's not tourists it's the Italians
coming to Starbucks there's a lot of
tourists coming into The Roastery but
yes it's and that they're choosing to
get their espresso at Starbucks not it
yeah yeah so I so and you know Italy I'm
going to Italy I think next week but
just for me the the the gratification
the satisfaction of you know complete
full circle from
1983 is just beyond belief from
I'm wondering another backdrop to The
Roastery and really throughout all the
2010s must have been third wave
coffee and I'm sure it was on your radar
screen yes at the same time it doesn't
seem like it's ever made a dent in
Starbucks there's always been stories
that all these competitors were going to
steal business from Starbucks but from
1983 to all the way today the
consumption of especially coffee is
still a small amount relative to the
macro opportunity so all those people
have expanded the market with and for
Starbucks now we created an industry
that didn't exist and they have followed
us and done really good things but we're
not threatened by that interesting so
you think third wave coffee brought
consumers into the Coffee Culture Market
yes that have then also become Starbucks
consumers and maybe they wouldn't have
been coffeee culture consumers at all
yes H how do you define third wave
coffee actually Howard is probably the
best person to ask I
mean it's a
very uh intentional independent coffee
store that is small enough that they're
roasting their own coffee or getting
coffee from a small proprietary roaster
M and creating a very
unique handcrafted
experience uh that in many ways
Starbucks can't do in scale right right
and so I I tip my hat to them but
there's no coffee experience in the
world that comes close to The Roastery
any of them and do those roasteries
Break Even or are they this like
marketing show piece that loses some
have some are making money and some
aren't wow I mean but I don't I you I
don't I've never viewed it that way
Billboards it's it's you can't you
couldn't put a price on the hundreds of
thousands of people that come into this
Roastery and have an experience of a
lifetime and I took Mr Arno Through The
Roastery really did yeah in Milan in
Seattle Seattle he and his son yeah wow
yeah spent a good amount of time with
him I've taken a lot
of of retail
CEOs and iconic business people through
the roas strey I bet who have who want
to see it wow wow what was Bernard doing
in Seattle I don't know what he was
doing in Seattle but I spent a feir
around time with him and his son the son
now runs Tiffany oh great wow and he his
level of curiosity was uh very high I
remember he was he kept looking at the
leather railing and the stitching and I
just said you spending a lot of time on
the
leather how bet he was maybe there's a
partnership to be
done um okay so now the the question
sort of becomes what are the setum
circumstances that had to be true in
order for Starbucks today to exist and
the one thing we haven't talked about or
one of the things is how much of what
Starbucks has accomplished could have
happened if it wasn't an addictive
substance like it's kind of this
incredible thing that it's a legal drug
that all the research anyone's ever done
into caffeine is by and large it's
neutral to helpful and like every other
drug that you know at some point people
have enjoyed whether it's smoking we
drinking more as research comes out over
time we find out shoot that wasn't good
for us that's not the case for coffee
what an amazing thing to get to build a
business on this delightful thing we
have to consume every day because we're
addicted and it's pretty good for us and
it gives you superpowers yeah I I'd like
to
believe it's not based on what you are
characterizing as an addictive beverage
I'd like to believe it's the experience
that has been created
around the enjoyment of the coffee and
the experience that
happens uh I also think and we we
haven't really spoke that much about it
is I can't State enough over the last
two decades what customization meant to
the company and how
customers created a personal beverage
well beyond what the menu was and I
don't know any other business yeah in
which the the incrementality of the
price has been dictated by the
consumer the base price is X but most
people are doing something in plus y i I
have a a very specific drink that I like
and when I go to coffee shops that are
not Starbucks I can't get it because it
feels taboo to order like I like an iced
almond milk latte with whipped cream and
when I go to most coffee houses want I'm
like I can't ask for wh wh cream on top
of that but Starbucks they're like of
course that's what we do
here this is something that I think has
translated incredibly well to the mobile
app and that no other food company has
really the level of customization and I
think the mobile app
actually added velocity to customization
it powered
customization Y and I think the
Starbucks Barista deserves so much
credit because they are are dealing with
so many different variations of
beverages some of which they're making
for the first time on the
Fly hard to do it's a hard work it has
to be a good number because there's I
don't know if it's I haven't done the
math billions trillions of combinations
of possible drinks and so it has to be
every single day as a barista you making
something for the first time yes I think
I the the the number that people use
inside the compy is
100,000 different variations of
beverages that are being made
consistently a 100,000 different
beverages wow this is actually a really
interesting way to lead into Playbook
because on the surface it's like an
obvious question right like yes it's an
addictive substance caffeine is of
course on the other hand you're in a
highly competitive market right selling
a commodity and the market actually is
not just coffee
it's let's stick with this theme it's
caffeine broadly which there's Coca-Cola
there's peps there's you know well not
only that but every food company every
retail Food business from McDonald's on
yeah took a page out of Starbucks went
to school on us right put espresso
machines in their stores and started
doing coffee beverages right that also
expanded the market and I think the real
question is for us here nobody has built
Starbucks despite decades in a highly
competitive market with whether it's
third wave or competitors in other
geographies or domestic competitors or
McDonald's getting into the business or
folders in Maxwell House there is a
unique tapestry that we've been weaving
throughout this episode that you know in
Hamilton Elmer's terms has power
here yes coffee so here's my second one
in addition to the the um it's a but
delightful it is perceived to be
virtuous to be a barista where it is not
perceived to be virtuous to flip burgers
and I don't know if that's something
Starbucks created I don't know if that's
something inherent to the product I
don't know if that's because it has this
Italian lineage but there's all these
incredible benefits that Starbucks and
any other Coffee House chains get to
enjoy because because it's respected to
do that work and I'm curious why do you
think that's respected when similar ways
of spending your hours in restaurant
work isn't first of all I've never heard
it quite like that and I think that's a
very interesting
insight there is craft and
art to the expression of making the
beverage I also think the intimacy of
the relationship with the customer is so
different and Baristas know the names of
their customers they know their dog's
name we have a drive-thru and I saw a
video where the Barista knows the name
of the dog and knows the it just the
whole thing is it's like a magical dance
that happens when the cars pull in and
all of a sudden it's not a transaction
one of the beauties that we've been we
have been able to do is Elevate the
experience of the drive-thru not all the
time so I think your question is steeped
in one is a commoditized environment and
the other clearly is not and the
challenge for Starbucks is continuing to
innovate for the Barista and when you in
this category to extend that point
you start from a place of this a good
job and you can sort of improve the
experience for that employee so they can
improve the experience for your
customers whereas in other things that
are commoditized they start from a
position of I have to do this job and
it's a really tough uphill battle to
invest in your people whereas Starbucks
kind of has a Tailwind but it is a hard
job certainly and we have to
honor the people who are doing it more
so today than ever before yep another
one that I have is it's funny it flies
in the face of some of the um pitfalls
of ubiquity that we were discussing
before the fact that it is everywhere uh
almost cheapens the experience to me
Starbucks's ubiquity is a massive
feature the fact that I can go anywhere
in the world and get basically my same
order or certainly anywhere in America
and get my same order I can even do it
from the mobile app in a way that I'm
very familiar with ordering uh it's
reliable it's predictable like it's the
same reason I bank with Chase and I buy
Apple products it's it's this thing that
I just know works everywhere and I never
have to you know take any risk on and
Starbucks didn't have that when it was
starting but it really feels like it's
reached this scale that no one else can
really compete with the level of
ubiquity so
ubiquity earlier on in our conversation
I said ubiquity is an enemy of Starbucks
and it's an enemy because we can't be
defined by our ubiquity we have to be
defined by the one store you come into
not based on the thousands but that
experience you have in the store yeah so
if the ubiquity is driving trust and
driving
convenience we have to ensure the fact
that we are providing that Intimacy in
the store and not allowing ubiquity to
commoditize the experience that that is
the framework of the daily challenge of
the
company frustratingly for those of us
who are trying to analytically put this
puzzle together the humanity is actually
the answer yeah scaling humanity is
actually the you know along with got
this long list here this obsessive
quality of product the fact that product
isn't just product but experience is the
product as it's everything you
experience around consuming the beverage
itself it's uh a bunch of the things
we've already talked about you invest in
your employees they take care of the
customers who takes care of the
shareholders but the shareholders are
last it's the fact that um oh yeah we
talked about the store cash flow
dynamics that you can scale in a really
cash efficient way when you know you're
paying the stores back in in less than
two years every time every store is a
billboard so you're intentionally
picking real estate in these places
where you're building familiarity with
people they're walking by over and over
and over you're extending the brand by
doing United Airlines by going to
grocery stores everything is a billboard
everything is a billboard yeah that's
the like why pay for customer
acquisition when you can you know
product in people's hands yeah um the
third place you know very novel idea at
first turned out that was something
basically the entire country and then
the the world wanted to participate in
not obvious at first and it's so easy to
think about these things that now we
take completely for granted like
Starbucks is in infrastructure in our
society it is assumed like when I go to
an airport or a city and there's not an
easy way to get to a store I'm like what
what is this place what Backwoods Place
am I in like it's it's it's expected and
when you live with something you know
most of your life you forget that it was
once a crazy idea I think that's the
yeah I think I think the other piece
that you didn't just list off there uh
that we've covered in depth is is you
know the cost go like investment in your
employees and the people and the
reduction of turnover and you know in in
Costco's case I think it's probably much
more so the reduction of turnover in
Starbucks's case it really is like
that's a a key the key element to
building the humanity right like I don't
know the employees at my Costco store no
what's the stat that you have on um I've
heard you say it a number of times on um
employee tenure at Starbucks versus
others in the category
it's a 2X is what I believe that
employee tenure is 2x longer or turnover
is half of what it is industrywide yes
it makes a huge difference and you've
talked about bean stock you've talked
about Comprehensive Health
Insurance when I think about the most
important thing we probably have done in
the last 20 years it's been the unique
relationship that we established with
Arizona State University and its
President Michael Crow could we create
free college tuition a 4-year free
college tuition through AR Ona state for
every single partner at Starbucks and we
did it and thousands of Starbucks
partners are engaged and going to school
and thousands have graduated the college
achievement plan demonstrates going back
to the early years of the speeches I was
giving about what is the responsibility
for a for-profit company in the world
we're living in and it's not just to
make
money here's one that we haven't talked
as much
about you were part of this secular
trend of gourmet coffee and I'm curious
if you
view that to be a true statement or if
you're saying no we created this entire
wave it wasn't going to happen it wasn't
just like I don't want to sound arrogant
at all but I think it's so clear that
Starbucks created an industry that did
not
exist
and as a result tens of thousands of
stores have followed in our wake and we
created an employment industry that did
not
exist not to mention that 5 million this
five million alone right yeah that's a
lot of people who have gone on to do
other things after and I think one thing
that's always been missed is that
Starbucks has always been a great first
job so in your mind then let's say
there's a parallel universe where Howard
Schultz doesn't
exist the year is
1995 is there
a
nationwide chain not called Starbucks
with Gourmet Coffee taking off in the
United States because the conditions
were perfect for
it I would assume that there would have
been a national
franchised business that would have
occupied the coffee space M but would
have been more commoditized a Dunkin
Donuts for instance yeah nothing I don't
think
anything would have been executed like
Starbucks but I think some someone would
have showed up right the opportunity was
just right too much white space the the
there was clearly demand there we were
coming off this horrible you know
folders in Maxwell House era and there
was this growing demand but that doesn't
mean that a company like Starbucks would
have been created it means just in some
way that consumer demand would have been
satisfied well you have to remember our
intent was not to build a global
business you know the first business
plan and I've I've said this many times
when I was raising money was a 100
stores and I I wasn't raising the money
and I didn't couldn't afford to reprint
the whole document whatever that was at
the time and I Whited it out no one's
even to know what that means I whiteed
out
75 when was the last time you used a
white out yeah it's been a while it's
been wait really so you yeah why did it
out 75 cuz I couldn't did it feel too
ambitious yeah people didn't believe I
think you're crazy but we never we we
you know Japan was the turning point of
thinking we could build an international
business but we we none of us had any
International experience no one in the
whole entire
company I mean in anyways you could say
this shouldn't have happened yeah okay
so this brings us to the absolute magic
of founder-led businesses mhm I mean
when you have a Founder at the helm you
get all this leeway from shareholders
from employees you can take crazy risks
and people know it's cuz you're you but
for you it wouldn't exist at all so run
with it what are the biggest innovations
that have happened at Starbucks not
under Howard
Schultz what a question
I'm pausing not because there hasn't
been
any uh because I'm sure there has
been but I'm hard pressed to kind of
think about what it
was I don't think you were uh running
the show when the pumpkin spice latte
came out yes I was you were I thought I
had one yeah yes I was I didn't like it
oh yeah it does feel like you were um
obsessed with the purity of the Italian
coffee bar for a long time and then at
some point you were like actually what
I'm obsessed with is serving customers
in whatever they want from us well the
ilali store only played Italian opera
and had no had no chairs I mean would
have scaled as well I'm recalling my
time from Rome two years ago that's
literally I'm walking around Rome and
that's everywhere yeah it's completely
different then no I think I had to see
the light I had to understand we were
not in business to please me please the
customers I mean what is it 70% of
drinks are now ice Beverages and it was
when you started 0% didn't have a cold
beverage for the first decade it was
Zero
yeah so to me there's this threat of um
at some point shaking off your own
opinions and saying we're going to do
what the customer wants us to do to a
degree
yeah but I was clearly leading there was
a leading question around Innovations
not under yeah so what's the point
what's the what's
your it's not it's not that there hasn't
been Innovation I
think uh there's a burden that the
organization has and a Reliance on the
founder that over time can become
unhealthy and not that I didn't want
succession I just I wasn't wasn't really
on my
mind and uh the the marketing and the
merchant mentality of Starbucks BS was
always with me and probably did not
allow others who were well intended and
could have done good things were
following and leaning on me which is not
the healthiest thing over the longevity
of the company and I think that has
covered up
mistakes that that's covered up things
and then was revealed when I
left I mean it's the very things that
make the business success uccessful the
founder bets that then at some point in
the company's second act kind of hold it
back you have all this muscle memory as
a company of relying on Founder Maverick
acts at some point you need to figure
out how as a company to
not well the the other thing about that
is most founder-led
companies are entrepreneurially
driven they're they're not it's not that
they're not following the rules they're
making the rules especially if you're
creating an industry that did not exist
founder leaves I'm not talking about me
historically and companies lose not only
the extent of the entrepreneurial
DNA but they lose the ability to be on
offense and the worst thing that a
company can do like a sports team is
start playing defense because you're
afraid to
fail that is a
disease not unlike another disease which
has happened at Starbucks which is ubis
the
worst thing that could happen to a
company is believing that you are
incapable of doing anything but
succeeding and you deserve the success
but if you start playing defense and
don't have the the offensive
mind it's it's not going to go well and
I think over time that has happened at
sterox you've transitioned from being
the CEO to someone else three different
times if you could go back let's even
just say the first time if you could go
back years 1999 or 1997 so you can start
working on some Talent Development um
what would you do differently to make
sure that
succession I would have believed Orin
when he said I only want to do this for
a couple years and I convinced myself I
could just get Orin to do this 5 years
maybe 10 years and so when he kept
saying you know I I want I don't want to
do this anymore I just so I was stuck
because I was not
prepared to look around the room and say
God I think he could do it and if I
would have spent maybe a year or two and
but I didn't I I was very I I believed
that I could convince norin to stay
longer and so I think and also Jim
Donald's a great guy but I I think the
immersion of an outside at that time
given we were moving into a
crisis not a Starbucks crisis but the
financial financial crisis very
difficult so it's on me I think when I
look back and I just did not do a very
good job of recognizing the internal
talent and cultivating it but I want to
I want to say one more thing about
Starbucks and it's the complexity of it
we're in multiple businesses so we're in
the agricultural business we are buying
coffee from 30 producing countries
around the world we are subject to
weather and the agricultural issues some
of which are many of which are not in
our control political all kinds of
stuff second we are
manufacturing a a
a commodity that is very very
challenging because it's coming from 30
producing countries and each coffee each
coffee from every country has its own
proprietary taste
profile that has to be roasted
differently and when you're blending it
like a winery it it's art and so we're
we're an agricultural
buyer we are a
manufacturer we are a
retailer we are a
wholesaler we are managing JV
relationships in 80 countries we have
JVS with two Behemoth companies Nestle
and pepsicola and above all else we are
in the people business managing the
behavior the motivation and the
opportunity creation for five almost
500,000
people and we're a public company in
which the expectations based on our
success are have been higher than
most not to mention your quasi fin
institution too yeah and we've got it
yeah all of that and uh and lastly I
think the the personal
responsibility of a Founder in my case
who loves this company as much as I love
my
family and so it's it's it's a
challenging fragile thing on a very
personal level and you can't escape
it you you made your point you want to
go somewhere and get I mean you can't
escape it so it's always around you I'm
so glad you're bringing this up it
really resonates to us hearing you say
that like it's the way we feel about
acquired in our show and like to imagine
like that's easy for us we have no
stakeholders we never would expect that
this would scale to 500,000 people if it
did I can't even imagine the complexity
of that but you also have now that
you've achieved this level of success
you you you have an expectation that
you've got to keep not Reinventing but
you've got to make sure that you're as
good as you've been no better you got to
be better again and your success is not
an entitlement like Starbucks just isn't
and and and when you have success it
gets harder because the bar keeps
getting higher yeah that's just human
expectations I going into this I was
thinking um I had some funny thing occur
to me which was at some point why does
Starbucks need to grow anymore it's
already everywhere and of course like
it's a public company so it it it
literally has just has to keep growing
but it's just human expectation that
things keep getting better than they
were last year they should should people
should just figure it out and make it
better we all think that about every
product and experience that we have
indeed well listeners we were thinking
about how to land this episode and you
know in our normal episodes we land the
plane in some way or come up with the
one thing you really you can't leave the
episode with without thinking about and
I feel like we covered a lot of those in
Playbook and so rather than drilling
into that again we were talking with
Howard and he threw out this idea I I
really do have one more thing to say
yeah given this moment that Starbucks is
in right now here in summer of 20124
this felt like the right way to address
that back to the interview well Howard
we're we're at the end here and uh I
think listeners may be wondering okay
but what about Starbucks today yeah and
the last few years have seen you know
you come back as an CEO for a year
transition to a new CEO it's been about
a year after that um and it's been a a
rough couple years I mean part of it is
coming out of the pandemic but um I
think anybody who tuned in the last
earnings call is wondering what's up
with the future of this company right um
can you give us a little bit of
narration on what brought you back the
things you did and where the company is
today yeah let me try and go back to
when I returned as an interim CEO in
April of
um I was asked by the board to come back
to the company and I I said no I I my my
life has changed I have I have no desire
to come back I have no intent to come
back but it was clear to me as the weeks
were going on that the company was
heading into a exential crisis and if
your listeners take anything away from
what we've talked about is my love of
the company is so significant that I I
changed my life and uh I came back to
the company now when I came
back and I want to be fair I don't want
to criticize anyone but when I came back
I saw things that really surprised me
about the lack of investment over a four
to five year period and also I didn't
like the way the stock BuyBacks were
were being used used to
basically uh increase
EPs and uh it's no way to run a company
so the First first day I came back and I
knew what the market would do is I I
announced that we were suspending the
stock BuyBacks and the stock went down I
expected it and I announced that we were
going to take basically the money we're
using to stock BuyBacks for the year and
I think was north of $2 billion and
invest back into the people of Starbucks
the partners which I did the most
important thing I did
though because I'm not a messiah but I
have an instinct about the company and I
know the inner workings of the company
better than anyone else I know the
people and so in a in a year's time
despite the underinvestment and the
challenges we we brought the company
back to a much healthier place
operationally and certainly the stock
price was significantly higher when I
left I think when I came back when I
when I started it was in the 70s when I
left it was you know but that's an
output that's investors voting on the
performance yeah yeah we don't have to
talk about stock price we don't want to
um
nevertheless um again
succession and
uh the board led a succession
process you have to remember I wasn't on
the board for f for long four or five
years and I resigned when I when I
decided
to leave the company after a year
despite the board asking me to stay
another year I just said I've I've done
my duty we have to find a new coo and so
they wanted you to be interim CEO for a
second yeah they wanted it was up it was
up to me and I I just that we and so the
board led a
search uh there was a number of
candidates uh laxman was chosen I met
him I approved his hiring uh but the
search Community was driving the process
so now we're a year
later um and I think we probably let's
just fast forward it hasn't been a great
year for Starbucks in fairness to laxman
there's a lot of external issues that
have contributed to the pressure like on
every company but the
company has not
executed the way that I think it should
have I go into the stores you know like
I I know the company and I think we're
we're not we're not our best right now
why did I write the
letter I didn't write the letter because
he had a bad interview on Kramer this on
LinkedIn yeah I wrote the letter because
I had written a couple of other
letters probably the iconic letter I
wrote was entitled the soul of the brand
and I was writing that letter because I
was a I don't get financial information
so I don't have any understanding
whether the company's making the cord or
not I was as surprised as anyone else to
see the dramatic
drop in revenue and in profit but I
wrote the soul of the brand because I
could smell
instinctively that there were things
going on that just did not feel right to
me that the shine was off the brand that
Partners were maybe not as inspired as
they had
been the first thing I want to say is
I've made it clear to the Starbucks
board Howard Schultz and I've made it
clear to lockman Howard Schultz has no
desire or intent
to return as CEO of Starbucks if you
want I'll say it again but I
don't but I can't
ignore what we've just discussed for the
last few hours if the company is do a
drift towards
mediocrity and I hold leadership and the
board responsible for that and my letter
was not accusatory my letter was not
predatory my letter was steeped in
counsel and advice based on 40 plus
years of experience in building this
company that's the advice in counsel I'm
giving you if you want to take the
advice it's up to you if you don't
you're responsible for the
outcome and so I'm I'm not I have no
operational role I'm not on the board
and I'm watching from afar in rooting
and cheering for Starbucks and I wrote
the letter in hope that it would be a c
cyst for a positive interpretation and
what were your recommendations in the
letter the one thing is we're not a
beverage company serving coffee we are a
coffee company serving
people and we need to be much more
coffee
forward and we cannot continue to
allow the mobile app to be a runaway
train that is going to cons consistently
lute the Integrity of the experience of
Starbucks we're not in the transaction
business we have to we have to execute
transactions but that has to go through
the lens of being an experienced
business an experienced place people are
longing for human connection even if
they're on a mobile app let's provide
it but I also recognize this is a
complex time it's difficult uh but
that's your job yeah
make
sense well to finish the
episode I can definitely say uh as a
unabashed fan the same way I opened the
episode um rooting for everyone over you
know few miles away to pull it off thank
you very much and I think you know
Starbucks is so
resilient uh Starbucks has had many many
challenges uh I have great faith in the
company and the equity of the brand and
the people who wear the cloth of the
company the green
apron y thanks Howard thanks Howard
thank you great really enjoyed it all
right well listeners thank you for being
on the journey with us that was super
fun to do with Howard remember the huge
announcement from the top of the show
San Francisco in September click the
link in the show notes to stay fully in
the loop on what that is when we are
able to share more details our good
friends at uh JP Morgan payments are um
cooking up something very cool with us
so stay tuned for more acquired.
fmsf or click the link in the show notes
to uh stay in the loop and of course
we'll be sharing this on uh Twitter and
probably talking about it on the podcast
again but find out more acquired.
fmsf if you want to talk about this
episode come to the slack acquired. FMS
slack and if you want to keep going with
acquired you're out of episodes you know
you you've uh decided that I've listened
to the entire back catalog and I really
wish a second show good news we have one
so check out acq 2 lots more interviews
there and I know the backlog and it's
only getting better from here and you
can imagine that having a great piece in
the Wall Street Journal and hitting
number one on Apple and Spotify which we
will reflect on at some point a totally
surreal few weeks here certainly um
prime the pump for a whole bunch of
great interviews that we've got coming
on
aq2 so uh with that a huge thank you to
our sponsors JP Morgan payments service
now and pilot.com Tom and listeners we
will see you next time we'll see you
next time who got the
truth is it you is it you is it you who
got the truth now huh
[Music]